Local structure that doesn’t require full
table representations
is important in both directed and undirected models.
How do we incorporate local structure into undirected models?
The framework for that is called “log-linear models” for reasons that will be clear in just a moment.
So
Whereas, in the original representation of the unnormalized density
we defined P tilde as the product of factors Φi(Di),
each [of] which is potentially a full table,
now we're going to shift that representation to something that uses a linear form.
So here's a linear form that is subsequently exponentiated,
and that's why it's called log linear—because the logarithm is a linear function.
So what is this form over here?
It's a linear function that has these things that are called coefficients.
And these things that are called features.
Features, like factors, each have a scope which is a set of variables on which the feature depends.
But different features can have the same scopes.
You can have multiple features all of which are over the same set of variables.
Notice that each feature has just a single parameter wj that multiplies it.
So, what does this give rise to?
I mean if we have a log linear model,
we can push in the exponent through the summation,
and that gives us something that is a product of exponential functions,
so you can think of each of these as effectively
a little factor,
but it’s a factor that only has a single parameter wj.
Since this is a little bit abstract, so let’s look at an example.
Specifically lets look at how we might represent a simple table factor as a log linear model.
So here’s a param, here’s a factor Φ, over two binary random variables X1 and X2.
And so a full table factor would have four parameters, A00, A01, A10, and A11.
So we can capture this model using a log linear model,
using a set of such of features, using a set of,
these guys, which are indicator functions.
So this is an indicator function.
It takes one if X1 is zero and X2 is zero,
and it takes zero otherwise.
So this the general notion of an indicator function.
It looks at the event—or constraint—inside the curly braces,
and it returns a value of 0 or 1, depending on
whether that event is true or not.
And so, if we wanted to represent this factor as a log-linear model,
We can see that we can simply sum up over all the four values of K and L,
which are either 0 or 1, each of them.
So were summing up over all four entries here.
And we have a parameter—or coefficient—w_kl which multiplies this feature.
And so, we would have a summation of w_kl:
of w00 only in the case where X1 is zero and X2 is zero.
So we would have x of negative w00 when X1=0 and X2=0,
and we would have x of negative w01 when
X1=0 and X2=1, and so on and so forth.
And it’s not difficult to convince ourselves that
if we define w_kl to be the negative log of the entries of the
corresponding entries in this table,
then that gives us right back the factor that
we defined to begin with.
So this shows that this is a general representation,
In the sense that we can take any factor and represent it as a log-linear model
simply by including all of the appropriate features.
But we don’t generally want to do that.
Generally we want a much finer grain set of features.
So let’s look at some of the examples of features that people use in practice.
So here are the features used in a language model.
This is a language model that we that we discussed previously.
And here we have features that relate:
First of all, let’s just remind ourselves [that] we have two sets of variables.
We have the variables Y which represent the annotations for each word
in the sequence corresponding to what category that corresponds to.
So this is a person.
This is the beginning of a person name.
This is the continuation of a person name.
The beginning of a location.
The continuation of a location, and so on.
As well as a bunch of words that are not—none of person, location, organization.
And they’re all labeled “other”.
And so the value Y tells us for each word what
category it belongs to,
so that we’re trying to identify people, locations, and
organizations in the sentence.
We have another set of variables X, which are the
actual words in the sentence.
Now we can go ahead and define…
We can use a full table representation that
basically tries to relate each and every Y that has a feature that has a full factor,
that looks at every possible word
in the English language,
but those are going to be very, very, expensive, and a
very large number of parameters.
And so we're going to define a feature that looks, for example,
at f of, say, a particular Y_i, which is the label for the i’th word in the sentence.
And X_i being that i’th word, and that feature says, for
example: Y_i equals person.
It’s the indicator function for Y_i equals person,
and X_i is capitalized.
And so that feature doesn’t look at the individual words.
It just looks at whether that word is capitalized.
Now we have just the single parameter that looks just at capitalization,
and parameterizes how important is capitalization for recognizing that something's a person.
We could also have another feature.
This is an alternative: This a different feature that can and could be part of the same model
that says: Y_i is equal to location,
Or, actually, I was little bit imprecise here—
This might be beginning of person. This might be beginning of location.
And X_i appears in some atlas.
Now there is other things that appear in the other atlas than locations,
but if a word appears in the atlas,
there is a much higher probability presumably that it’s actually a location
and so we might have, again, [a] weight for this feature
that indicates that maybe increases the probability in Y_i being labeled this way.
And so you can imagine that constructing a very rich set of features,
all of which look at certain aspects of the word,
and rather than enumerating all the possible words
and giving a parameter to each and one of them.
Let’s look at some other examples of feature-based models.
So this is the example from statistical physics.
It’s called the Ising model.
And the Ising model is something that looks at pairs
of variable. It’s a pairwis Markov [inaudivle].
And looks the pairs of adjacent variables, and basically
gives us a coefficient for their products.
So now, this is the case where
variables are in the end are binary, but
not in the space zero one that rather
negative one of and positive one. And so o
now, we have a model that's [inaudible] as
features that are just the product of the
values of the adjacent variables. Where
might this come up? It comes up in context
for example, of modeling the spin of
electrons in a grid. So here you have a
case where the electrons can rotate either
along one direction or in the other
direction so here is a bunch of blo, the,
the, the atoms that are marked with a blue
arrow. You have one rotational axe season,
the red arrow rotating in the opposite
direction. And you, and this basically
says we have a term that, who, probability
distribution over the joint set of spin.
So this is the joint, the joint. Spins.
And the model, depends on whether adjacent
atoms have the same spin or opposite spin.
So notice that one times one is the same
as -one times -one. So this really just
looks at whether they have the same spin
or different spins. And there is a
parameter that looks at, you know, same or
different. That's what this feature
represents. And depending on the value of
this parameter over here, if the parameter
goes one way, we're going to favor systems
that, where the atoms spin in the same
direction. And if its going in the
opposite direction, you're going to favor
atoms that spin in a different direction.
And those are called ferromagnetic and
anti-ferromagnetic. Furthermore, you can
define in these systems an ocean of a
temperature. So the temperature here says
how strong is this connection? So notice
that as T grows, as the temperature grows,
the WIJs get divided by T. And the all
kind of go towards zero. Which means that
the strength of the connection between
adjacent atoms, effectively becomes almost
moot, and they become almost a couple from
each other. On the other hand as the
temperature decreases. Then the effect of
the correl-, of the interaction between
the atoms becomes much more signifigant.
And they're going to impose much stronger
constraints on each other. And this is
actually a model of a real physical
system. I mean, this is real temperature,
and real atoms, and so on. And sure
enough, if you look at what happens, to
these models as a function of temperature,
what we see over here is high temperature.
This is high temperature and you can see
that there is a lot, you know, there's a
lot of mixing between the two types of
spin and this is low temperature and you
can see that there's much stronger
constraints in this configuration about
the spins of adjacent atoms. Another kind
of feature that's used very much in, lots
of practical applications is the notion of
a metric, of a metric feature, an M.R.S.
So what's a metric feature? This is
something that comes up, mostly in cases
where you have a bunch of random variables
at. That all take values in some joint
labels, so for example they might all be
[inaudible]. They all might take values
one, two, three, four. And what we'd like
to do is [cough] we have, when we have x I
that are connected to each other, x I and
x j that are connected to each other by an
edge. We want x I and xj to take. Values.
So in order to enforce the fact that X
[inaudible] take similar values we need an
ocean of similarity. And we're going to
encode that using the distance function U,
that takes two values, one for XI and one
for XJ, and says, how close are they to
each other? So what does the distance
function need to be. Well, the distance
function needs to satisfy the standard
condition on a distance function or a
metric so first is reflexivity. Which
means that if the two, if the two
variables take on the same value, then
that distance better be zero. Oh I forgot
to say that this, sorry, this needs to be
a non-negative function. Symmetry means
that, That the distances are symetrical.
So the distance between two values D1 and
D2 are the same as the distance between D2
and D1. And finally, is the triangle
inequality, which says that the distance
betwen D1 and D2, so here is D1 here is
D2, and the distance between D one and D2
is less than the distance between D1 and
D3 and then going to D2. So the standard
triangle inequality. If a, if a distance
just satisfies these two conditions, it's
called a semi metric. Otherwise, if it
satisfies all three, it's called a metric.
And both are actually used in practical
applications. So how do we take this,
distance feature and put it in the context
of an MRF? We have a feature that looks at
two variables, XI and XJ. And that feature
is the distance between XI and XJ. And
now, we put it together by multiplying
that with a coefficient. W. I. J., such
that, W.I.J. Has to be greater than zero.
So that we want, the metric M.R.S. So
what, the effect that, that has is that,
the lower. The distance. The higher. This
is, because of the negative coefficient,
which means that higher the probability.
Okay? So. The, the more pairs you have
that are close to each other and the
closer they are to each other the higher
the probability of the overall
configuration. Which is exactly what we
wanted to have happen. So conversely if
you have very, values that are far from
each other in the distance metric the
lower the probability in the model. Here
are some examples of metric mrf. One the
simplest metric mrf is one that gives the
distance of zero when the two classes are
equal to each other and the distance of
one every where else. You know just like a
step function. This gives rise to a
potential that looks like this. So we have
0's on. The diagonal. So we get a bump in
probability when the two adjacent
variables take on the same label and
otherwise we get a reduction in
probability. But it, but it doesn't matter
what particular value they take. That's
one example of a simple, metric. A
somewhat, more expressive example might
come up when the values V are actually
numerical values. In which case, you can
look at maybe the, difference between the
miracle values. So, VK minus VL. And you
want, and when VK is equal to VL. The
distance is zero, and then you have a
linear, function that increases the
distance as the distance between V.K. And
V.L. Grows. So, this is the absolute
value. A VK minus the L. A more
interesting notion that comes up a lot in
practice is, we don't want to penalize
arbitrarily things that are far way from
each other in label space. So this is what
is called as truncated. When you are
penalty and you can see that beyond a
certain thresh hold. There, the penalty
just becomes constant, so it plateaus. So
that there is a penalty, but it doesn't
keep increasing over, as the labels get
further from each other. One example where
metric MRFs are used, is, when we're doing
image segmentation. And here, we tend to
favor segmentations where adjacent
superpixels. So these are adjacent
superpixels. And we want them to take the
same class. And so here we have no penalty
when the super pixels take the same class
and we have some penalty when they take
different classes. And this is actually a
very common, albeit simple, model for
image segmentation. Let's look at a
different MRF, also in the context of, of
computer vision. This is and MR-, an MRF
that's used for image denoising. So here
we have a noisy version of a real image
that looks like this. So this is, you can
see this kind of, white noise overlayed on
top of the image. And what we'd like to
do, is we'd like to get a cleaned up
version of the image. So here we have, a
set of variables, X, that correspond to
the noisy pixels. And we have a set of
variables, 'y', that corresponds to the
clean pixels. And we'd like to have a
probabilistic model that relates, X and, X
and Y. And what we're going to is we'd
like, so, in [inaudible], I mean,
[inaudible] the, the, so you'd like to
have two effects on the pixels Y. First,
you'd like YI to be close, [inaudible], my
I to be close to XI. But if you just do
that, then you're just going to stick with
the original image. So what is the main
constraint that we can employ on the image
in order to clean it up is the fact that
adjacent pixels tend to have the same
value. So in this case what we're going to
do is we're going to model we're going to
constrain the image so that we're going to
constrain the Yi's to try and make Yi
close to its neighbors. And the further
away it is, the bigger the penalty. And
that's the metric MRF. Now we could use
Just the linear penalty. But, that's going
to be a very fragile Model, because, not
obviously the right answer isn't the model
where all pixels are equal to each other
in their actual intensity value because
that would be just a single grayish
looking image. So when you look
[inaudible], one pixel be part of its
adjacent pixel it's getting [inaudible] in
a different direction either by it's own
observation or by other adjacent pixels.
So the right model to use here is actually
the [inaudible] model and that one is
commonly use for using [inaudible].
Interesting, almost exactly the same idea
is used in the complex of stereo
reconstruction. There, The values that you
like to infer, the Yi's, are the depth
disparity for a given pixel in the image,
how deep it is. And here also we have
spacial continuity. We like the depth of
one pixel to be close to the depth of an
adjacent pixel. But once again we don't
want to enforce this too strongly because
you do have [inaudible] dexterity in the
image and so eventually you'd like things
to be allowed to break away from each
other. And so once again, one typically
uses some kind of truncated, linear model.
For doing the [inaudible] construction,
often [inaudible] by other little tricks.
So, for example, here we have the actual
pixel appearance, for example, the color
and texture are very similar to each
other, you might want to have the stronger
constraint similarity. Versus if the color
and texture of the adjacent pixels are
very different from each other they may be
more likely to belong to different objects
and you don't want to enforce quite as
strong of a similarity constraint.