In this segment I'm going to show you,
that dependency syntax is a very natural
representation, for relation extraction
applications. One domain of which a lot of
work has been done on relation extraction
is in the biomedical text domain. So here
for example, we have the sentence that the
results demonstrated that KC interacts
rhythmically with [inaudible], KA and KB.
And what we?d like to get out of that is a
protein interaction event. So here's the
interacts that is sort of indicates the
relation and these are the proteins
involved. And there are a bunch of other
proteins as well. Well, the point we get
out of here, is that if we can, have this
kind of dependency syntax. And it's very
easy starting from here to follow along
the arguments of the subject and the
preposition with and to easily see the
relation that we'd like to get out, and if
we're just a little bit cleverer, we can
then also follow along the conjunction
relations and see that KC is also
interacting with these other two proteins.
And that's something that a lot of people
have worked on. In particular, one
representation that's being widely used
for relation extraction applications in
biomedicine is the Stanford dependencies
representation. So the basic form of this
representation is as a projective
dependency tree. And it was designed that
way so it could be easily generated by
post processing of phrase structure trees.
So if you have a notice of hiddenness in
the phrase structure tree, the Stanford
dependency software provides a set of
matching pattern rules that will then type
the dependency relations and give you out
a Stanford dependency tree. But Stanford
dependencies can also be a now
increasingly odd generated, generated
directly by dependency [inaudible], such
as the [inaudible] that we looked at
recently. Okay so this is roughly, what
the representation looks like. So it's
just as we saw before, with the words
connected by type dependency arcs. But
something that has been explored in the
Stanford dependencies framework, is,
starting fro m that basic dependencies
representation. Let's make some changes to
it to facilitate relation extraction
applications. And the idea here is to
emphasize the relationships between
content words that are useful for relation
extraction applications. Let me give a
couple of examples. So, one example is
that. Commonly you'll have a content word
like based, and where. The company here is
based Los Angeles, and it's separated by
this preposition in, or function word, and
you can think of these function words as
really functioning like case markers in a
lot of other languages. So it's seen more
useful if we directly connect it based LA,
and we introduce the relationship of prep
in. And so, that's what we do, and we
simplify the structure. But there are some
other places, too, in which we can do a
better job at representing the semantics
with some modifications of the graph
structure, and so a particular place of
that is these coordination relationships.
So we very directly got here that. Bell
makes products, but we'd also like to get
out that Bell distributes products, and
one way we could do that, is by,
recognizing, this and relationship and
saying Okay, well that means that Bell,
should also, be the subject of
distributing. And what they distribute, is
products. [sound]. And similarly down
here, we can recognize, that they're,
they're computer products, as well as
electronic products. So we can make those
changes, to, to the graph, and get a kind
of reduced graph representation. Now, once
you do this, there are some things that
are not as simple. In particular, if you
look at this structure, it's no longer a
dependency tree. Because we have multiple
arcs pointing at this node, and multiple
arcs pointing at this node. But on the
other hand, the relations that we'd like
to extract are represented much more
directly. And let me just show you one
graft that gives an indication of this.
So, this was a graph that was. Originally
put together by [inaudible] et al, who
were the team that won the Bio NLP 2009
shared l relation extraction, using as the
representational substrate, Stanford
dependencies. And what they wanted to
illustrate with this graph is how much
more effective dependency structures were
at linking up the words that you wanted to
extract in a relation, than simply looking
for words in the linear context. So, here
what we have is that this is the distance
which can be measured either by just
counting words to the left or right. Or by
counting the number of dependency arcs
that you have to follow. And this is the
percent of time that it occurred. And so
what you see is, if you just look at
linear distance. There are lots of times
that there are arguments and relations
that you want to connect out that are
four, five, six, seven, eight words away.
In fact, there's even a pretty large
residue here of well over ten percent
where the linear distance away in words is
greater than ten words. If on the other
hand though, you, I try and identify,
relate the arguments of relations by
looking at the dependency distance, then
what you discover is that the vast
majority of the arguments are very close
by neighbors in terms of dependency
distance. So that 47 percent of them are
direct dependencies and another 30 percent
of distance too. So take those together
and that's greater than three quarters of
the dependencies that you want to find.
And then this number trails away quickly.
So there are virtually no. Arguments of
relations that aren't fairly close
together in dependency distance and it's
precisely because of this reason that, you
can get a lot of mileage, in, doing
relation extraction by having a
representation like dependency syntax.
Okay, I hope that?s given you some idea of
why knowing about syntax is useful, when
you want to do various semantic tasks in
natural language processing.