Okay, so let's have a look at some
applications of Bayesian games now beyond
the conflict example that we had looked at
before. And one of the areas that
understanding in incomplete information
games has made a huge impact as in
understanding auctions and incentives to
bid an auction. So let's have a look.
We'll start with a very simple version of
auction and then we will actually look at
some more complicated versions of auctions
and more realistic versions as we go
along. Let's start with a simple version.
So we have two bidders. They're bidding
for painting and we'll look at what's
known as a first price auction and we'll
think of a sealed bid auction okay so they
each in this case have a value for the
painting so the type of the players is
Theta I. And it, it just specifies how
much they're willing to pay for the
painting. How much do they value the
painting? So, let's, keep things simple.
Let's suppose that they have a value of
either two or three, say, dollars or
thousands or millions, what-, whatever you
like. So they either value the, the
painting at two or three. And, equal
likelihood. So there's a half a
probability that they wake up, and they
think the painting's worth two. Half a
probability that they wake up, the
painting's worth. Three, and we'll think
of this as IID. So, if I wake up, and I
think the painting's worth two, the chance
that the other proba-, the other person
thinks it's worth two or three is an even
coin flip. So what I end thinking is
completely independent of whatever they
like. How much they like the painting. So
our tastes are completely [inaudible] wake
up, we decide how much we like the
painting. And now we have to put a bid in
an envelope, and send it off to the
seller. So, first price auction. What does
that mean? First price means the highest
bidder wins and they pay their bids, so
first highest price is the winner and pays
that particular bid. Okay, so, let's think
of a game now. We got a basing game. We
know what the types are. There are either
two or three with equal prob ability, the
players have to bid in whole integers, and
in this case in terms of specifying
payoffs it's quite simple what you pay off
its how much you value the painting minus
how you pay so if you win the option
you're going to get Theta I. Minus your
bid. If you lose you get zero right so the
payoffs are going to depend on what the
actions are which will determine first of
all if you end up having the highest bid
or not and what you get is. If you win,
you get your, your, your value minus how
much you bid. If you lose, you just get
zero. Okay? So this is a fully symmetric
world. So let's keep our life simple, and
look for a symmetric equilibrium. And
we'll look for one in pure strategies. So
what we need to do is specify, so in a
symmetric equilibrium, we. Have each
player just we need to specify what they
would do if they had a value of three what
they would do if they had a value of two
and so that no player would chose to
change their bid if they were both bidding
that way so they're both happy maximizing
their payoff, expected payoff. Given these
bids, if this was the situation. ... >>
Well, let me just say a, a couple of words
about, you know, looking for equilibria,
searching for equilibria in these kinds of
games, symmetric, asymmetric, and so
forth. So, you know, th-, there's no easy
recipe for always finding equilibria. So,
in worse case scenario is when you're
faced with games you might have to just
actually, you know, exhaustively look
through what are all the possible
combinations of strategies that are
possible. And, and solve and find out
which ones are equilibria. Some. You know
it's, it's, it's [inaudible]. A little bit
of an art in the sense that there are
things that we know about the structure of
the games that give us hints as to how to
proceed. And here we have a fully
symmetric setting. And fully symmetric
settings generally though exist a
symmetric equilibrium at least when in
mixed strategies and sometimes in pure
strategies so that's a useful starting
point. And then we can go through and use
some logic to try and thin the field down
in terms of what we might be looking for.
So it's a little bit like looking for
solutions to differential equations. There
are different rules. Of thumb. There's
structure which helps you guess, how to
proceed, but largely there's no easy and.
Set and however them, they're always going
to find you know, equilibrium easily for
you. Sometimes you gonna have to struggle
a lil bit and, and search through. But
here we have a nice simple setting. It's a
symmetric setting. That gives us an idea
of what, how to proceed. So, we look for
symmetric equilibrium, and basically what
we've to do is specify what should a
person do and they're whenever value of
three what, how should they verify a value
of two. Okay. So first of all, one thing
to note, so we, again, they, they have to
bid whole integers we can try various
combinations. So you, you never want to
bid more than your value, because then if
you end up winning, you're paying more
than you value the, the object at. You're
going to be getting negative payouts.
You're better off just not bidding at all
or bidding zero. So you, the second bid
that we might. You'll consider is what if
you bid your actual value so if I have a
value of three and I bid three then my
payoff is zero no matter what so if I lose
I get a payoff of zero if I win I am
paying Theta I minus my bid right so if I
win if I am bidding my value I'm going to
get zero. If these two things are equal,
so in, in, in that case, my pay-off is
zero no matter what. So basically in, in a
first-price auction, it's going to be in,
in players' interests to shade their bids.
What does that mean? To, to bid less than
their value in hopes that, when they win
the object, they're paying less than they
value it at, and they're getting some pay,
positive pay-offs, okay? So, a natural
thing to try is that they're gonna bid,
when their value is three, they're going
to bid something less than three, with, in
hopes of winning some pay-off. And, when
their value i s two, they're going to bid
less than. Too. So we can start by looking
for an equilibrium of that form. Well,
that's an easy one to try. Let's try
bidding one below your value, in this case
we'll bid when your values three bid two,
when your value is two bid one. So let's
check. We just want to check if this is a
symmetric equilibrium. So if the other
player is bidding according to this, if
theta I is three and the other player uses
this strategy, what's my expected utility?
Well, if I build three. I'm getting, we,
we already just went through this. I, I'm
always gonna get zero. So win or lose no
matter what I'm gonna get a payoff of
zero. If I lose I get zero. If I, if I win
I'm bidding my full value, I get nothing
out of it so that gives me a payoff of
zero. If I bid two, what happens? Well,
when I do win. I'm going to get my value
of three. The price I pay is two. So this
is the bid. This is my theta I, so my
value is, is three minus two. What's the
probability that I win? Well the
probability, there's a 50, 50 chance that
the other person is a low type or a high
type. If their bidding according to this
function there's a half a probability that
their going to bid. One and a half a
probability that they did two. So if I'm
bidding two there's one half probability
that I win outright. And there's a half a
chance that we tie. And if we tie, we have
the seller just flip a coin, and decide
randomly who wins. So there's a half a
chance that we tie, and then a half a
chance that I win the coin flip. So I end
up winning with a probability a quarter.
So what's my overall value from this?
Three quarters. What would happen if I bid
one instead? Well, if I bid one instead I
get a higher value here so when I do win,
I'd end up with paying less. That's great.
I get the painting for less but the chance
that I win is now only when I match, so if
I'm bidding one the only time I'm gonna
win is when the other person bids one and
I win the coin flick. So there's a half a
chance that the other person bids one, and
half a chance t hat they win the coin
flip. Overall probability of a quarter. So
here, 3-1-2, a quarter. We end up with a
value of one-half. So here, you know, I
end up, I'm better off bidding two than
bidding one. And if I bid zero, well, I'm
never gonna win. The other person's always
bidding above zero. I get a payoff of
zero. So here, my unique best response, if
the other person is bidding according to
this unique best response. One Theta I is
= three is to bid two right so if the
other person is bidding two and one in
this manner then indeed when I have a
value of three then I do want to bid two
so that holds together okay. So we also
need to check that the bid of one when
your type is two is the best response, we
can go through there. Well what happens
if, if I bid three, I'm bidding above my
value, so I'm going to get, whenever I
win, I get a payoff of minus one and now
I'm outbidding the other player all the
time so I'm going to win for sure. I'm
going to get a payoff of minus one. If I
did too well. >> Win or lose, it doesn't
matter. I get zero because I'm always
bidding, my full value so even when I win
I don't get anything. If I bid zero, I
lose for sure, so the only really bid that
makes sense in this case is bidding one.
Here, I get some positive value when I
win. I win with probably a quarter, right?
I win when the other type is actually a
low type, also bidding one. And then I win
the coin flip. So I end up with the value
of a quarter. So here, my unique best
response. Is when Theta I is equal to two
to bid one. So indeed we've checked that
if the other player's following these
strategies in fact I strictly care to
follow these strategies these are my
unique best responses so this is an
equilibrium and. It's a symmetric, pure
strategy Bayesian equilibrium. It's a
strict equilibrium so it's a strong
equilibrium and so basically Bayesian
equilibrium has given us an analysis of
this game which allows us to make
predictions. In this case the better is
the low shade their values. How much lower
than the value t hey bid so that here that
when your. Type three, you bid two. When
you're type two, you bid one. This gives
us some idea of how things might work in
an auction. We'll take a look at a little
more elaborate example of an auction next.
That'll give us a little more insight into
what's going on. But this illustrates the
basic definitions, and allows us to see
how things proceed.