Hi, everyone. You know, that most of you
still working really hard on the last
couple of assignments and problem sets but
nevertheless now NOP class is coming to
its close and so we thought we'll both
update you on a few of the issues. And
first of all, [inaudible] always interest
in numbers so let's say it's just about
the numbers. So, it seems like. As we come
in to week 7's material of the problem
that's in programming assignments. It
seems like there are about 5,000 people
still actively watching the videos and
about 2,000 people doing all the work at
the home works. But that's, you know,
overall has just been enormous amount of
stuff going on so it now have well over a
million video views and all. Yeah, it's
very exciting. For homework six. The
parsing homework was definitely our
hardest homework so far and there were
definitely problems with the codes being
under commented so we appreciate very much
those of you who helped out each other in
the forums and made things very clear for
each other. Those of you who managed to
finish the homework have a lot to pull
this so they got along out of it. But
those of you who didn't have the time to,
to do all of it. We encourage you to do
come back and do put them in homework
seven and eight which are much easier than
homework six and should be a lot fun as
well. One of the things that some people
have been asking about is, hey, can we
take those great passes that we did write
for [inaudible] assignment six and keep on
working on them by posting them on
[inaudible] or some of the site like that.
There is a slight problem with that
because, you know, we are hoping that
we're gonna do this cause again sometime
in the future and we'd like to be have to
reuse some of the assignments so I'd
really prefer that they're just that great
solutions to all the assignments sitting
on the open web and to keep some of that
stuff on the forum sites for the class.
So, it's great that people. Want to keep
exploring and doing better things for NOP
but. We really think this probably a be
tter idea for you to pick out one of the
several open source NLP frameworks that
out there and look at ways in which you
can contribute to that because that both
doesn't sort of conflict with our
assignments but actually gonna be more
useful for you and people around the world
in general if you're helping along these
open source frameworks. So there are good
ones, the Python and LTK is the best known
one and there are several well-known,
Java, NLP Open Source Frameworks which
certainly includes our own stand for NLP
tools but also other things like Open NLP,
the Gate NLP Framework. [inaudible] I'll
just [inaudible] out there [inaudible]
out. Okay and that. Rings up the issue of
all, what's gonna happen with this class
website after the class ends. It is gonna
stay open and available and all you guys
will be have to keep on looking at stuff
and referencing things and even beyond
that, what we're also gonna have is this
gonna be available in the Archive Mode.
So, people who haven't been registered in
the class, you also have to look at the
content in terms of the videos that are up
there and they are not program and the
assignments which were entertainment gonna
keep to the people who were enrolled in
the class. But you shouldn't worry about
things going away. Yes and those of you
who are enrolled, can still, the formal
stay up, we encourage you to continue to
talk to each other in the forms. Those of
you who never got to finish some of the
home works, keep working on the home
works, go ahead and post them the site
will stay up and then. For, for new people
who will eventually be teaching the class
again but meanwhile we'll be leaving the
videos up so if your friends wanna watch
the videos, we encourage that. And then
eventually we'll actually teach the class
again. In fact for. Everybody has been
really helpful on the forums that, we
mentioned this earlier about helping
people out with, with the code, helping
people out with basic NLP. It's been very
supportive community and we really
appreciate that and we think it's really
great. We'd like help from you in
suggesting, you have already given us
suggestions for next year but I put up a,
a forum just now that we'd like you give
us specific suggestions about ways we can
make the course better for next year. We
know Homework six is one of them but
there's lot of suggestions you've given.
About improving the problem sets or other
reading material we can suggest or
anything else that will help us improve
our course for the second time we teach it
that would be great. We all have dreams of
the future where there are computers with
full natural language understanding in and
our research we still variously hoped to
work to those goals but in terms of the
practical NLP does applies around the
world at the moment, really you guys are
just seeing the ton of the stuff that you
actually used. Things like fix
classifiers, building sequence
classifiers, [inaudible] and other things,
parsers questions answering, machine
techniques. So, really should feel good if
you made your way through this class that
you confident practitioner of the kind of
[inaudible]. Techniques, the leading to a
new cost of more intelligent language
wielding computer applications and so we
hope that you'll be able to take these
ideas and knowledge and they'll often. And
go often apply them in many different
places including this world now by human
language material is just everywhere over
the web as part of the new move to the. >>
Content authoring and social computing
that's going on everywhere. So much of
that is about language use so now you have
a good tool kit to be able to go off and
do things with that material and we hope
that you'll be able to find good things to
do. >> Yeah. Thanks for taking the class
and look forward to seeing you wherever
and whenever we see you. Thanks a lot.