Hi everyone. Welcome to our instructed
chat. We thought we'd take the opportunity
to have a bit of a chance to check in with
students and tell them a bit about the
cause and a couple of issues in the class.
I'm Christopher Manning. And I'm Dan
Giraffeski. Okay. So, first of all, some
people are just being, asking for some
statistics about the class. So let's just
give some rough numbers for how things are
going. Maybe later in the class, we'll get
a class survey up, and get a bit more
information. But the original
registrations was about 60,000 people, and
about 40,000 people, created accounts. But
then if you're actually wondering, like,
here we are at the end of week four. How
many people are really doing stuff?
Watching all the videos or also doing the
assignments. It seems like we've got about
6,000 people who are watching the videos
each. Week and about 4,000 are submitting
the programming assignments. So that's
pretty exciting number of you actually
doing the homework which is really great
for us to see. Cool, So let's see,
There've also been a few questions about,
you know, some of this stuff about the
policy of closing registrations and so on.
Oh, yes, and so we, we're happy to tell
you that they've allowed us to open up all
the videos now for previewing. So if your
friends aren't registered and you'd like
them to be able to see the class, they can
actually watch all the videos and take the
in-video quizzes just by clicking on the
home page, on the, on the preview. The, I
guess there's a button called preview. So
have them check that out. And then there
are a couple of issues that kind of, come
up quite a bit on the forum, which we
think are really at the heart of how.
Modern natural language processing works,
and there are important reasons why it
works this way, and we just thought we'd
spend a little bit of time talking about,
and I think they're good to talk about,
because there are things that are so much
second nature to us, that we normally
don't think about them, because of course
you should do t hings this way, for tasks
like natural language processing. But we
can see that for. Students coming to this
for the first time in fact it's different
to most other things and can seem really
confusing why things are the way they are
and so the first of these is this set up
where we have training sets, div sets and
then hidden test sets. So I know at first
some of you guys thought gee that's just
unfair. They are gonna grade us for four
months on data that we've never seen, that
can't be reasonable nor nice to do things.
But this set up is really at the heart and
soul of modern empirical natural language
processing. So the whole Self Ed is, is
what we'd like to do is write algorithms
that will work well on a new different
data in the future. So the idea is that
you are building something like a sediment
classifier which is wanting to save a
camera models of y foot not liked. But you
know, it's just not of interest whether it
can give the right answers for the
collection of tweets that you build your
model over. What's of interest is, is this
model gonna work well on the tweets that
are posted next week. And that's the sense
in which we want to have a hidden test
set. And in particular for the kind of
classifiers we build, it's really, really
easy to get classifiers that work well on
the particular data that you're building
on, them over. That by having rich
features, putting in matching conjunctions
of terms, regular expressions with main
lists of all the names that you happen to
see in the training data, that those
things will fit a particular set of
training data really closely. And if you
keep on adding more and more features, you
can make it if you want so you get the
training data 100. To send rights and well
then you can test it out on dev data and
you know it's the extent of their stuff
the stiffen in the dev date. Well if you
want to you could stop putting that in
your classifiers as well and do really
well in the dev data. But, That stuff is
not interesting unless you're producing a
system which will ac tually also work well
on other data that you have never seen
before. And so what that means is that a
lot of assessing nat-, natural language
processing systems is really about whether
your models generalize. As to whether
you've built in important features of
language and the way it is used, in such a
way that your systems will actually work
on other sets of data in the future. And
maybe Dan can say a bit more about that,
[inaudible], and how that works out with
the iii... Yeah, so, so at least one of
you asked on the form, well, suppose I
just take. Let's say for, homework four.
Suppose I take some names that were in the
depth set, and add them into my training
set. It's a little bit cheating, but
wouldn't that be a good idea in general?
And the reason why it's a bad idea is
that, although you'll do very well on the
training set and depth set, you're gonna
train a feature and learn a weight for
that feature that really over trusts your
list of names. It'll say, that list of
names is fabulous, Because every name in
my training set. There it is in my little
list of names. I'm going to assign that
feature a huge weight. Now I get to my
test set, and all of my other features
have much lower weights, and we should
have been trusting those other features,
because my name list doesn't have any the
names in my test set. So it's very
important to be thinking about the test
set and about generalization to data you
haven't seen. I want to say just a little
bit more of the dangers of over fitting.
Cause this one really comes up both when
you're doing research and in real life.
That what happens is, we're wanting to try
and work out how well something performs
in truth. But if you have some fixed set
of data that you're assessing performance
on, then what happens is, as you develop a
system, you progressively. Overfit your
system to that particular set of data and
so the numbers that you're getting are
unrealistically good. So the way that,
that happens is that even if you say,
well, here's my, my set of dev data over
ther E. I've never looked at it. I don't
know what names it contains. The natural
inclination is, you try out various
models, you change the smoothing, you add
more features, all the kinds of things
we've been talking about. And human nature
is that when you make these changes, that
every time you make a change that. Lifts
the numbers on your test set. You keep
that change. And every time you make a
change that doesn't improve your numbers,
you drop that change. And well, the
problem is that a lot of those changes
will just be making you do better on the
dev set for no good reason That you're not
actually producing a system that's better.
Data in the statistically significant way,
it's just the changes that you made happen
to work on this one particular set of
data. And if you iterate over that twenty
times, you then sort of, ten of the
changes work and you've pushed up your
numbers on the depth set ten times but.
And maybe your sister is actually no
better in fundamentals. And so the only
way to assess that is to have a separate
set of final test data. That you can say,
well are their numbers better on this
final test set? And in the ideal case you
only ever run once on that final test set.
And you can then say it's a pretty good
measure of performance. Now in the real
world you know, it tends to be that.
Things aren't quite that perfect 'cause,
you know, you'll have make. Run one, the
one system, think it's good, run it on the
final test set, and then suddenly you have
some ideas, some other things you could
put in, and you do put them in, and they
work out on the desk set, so you think
okay, I'll run it again, on the final test
set, and low and behold it goes up. And
you know, to some extent everyone does
that a little bit, and then ends up using
the test set two, or three, or four times,
but it's really important to realize that
you know, if you stop doing That too much.
Well, then, again, you're just having this
problem that you're over fitting to the
test set and that you're, reporting
unrealistically good perf ormances. And so
that's one of the reasons that in the L-P
community, that there's this really strong
tra-, tradition of having shared tasks.
Where there's a task that's set up by some
organizers, in which they give out
training data and people are meant to come
up with systems, which will then be run on
fresh test data. And one of the things
that happens again and again in these
competitions is that some things that
people have claimed worked well in papers,
actually end up working terribly. And
there's just over and over again, a big
difference shown between systems that
actually really work, when they're just
run afresh on new data versus systems that
people manage to get to work on some
particular data set, once they've spend
three months tweaking every parameter so
that it works well on that data set. So
we've been, in general, very happy with
you guy's participation of forms,
everybody's helping answer each other's
questions and, and so it's great to see
everybody out there. We're on the forms as
well. And so keep up that. Work and please
feel free to make suggestions, ask us
questions. We try to take into account any
suggestions you make as we are recording
videos and as we're modifying, fixing bugs
in probably homeworks and problem sets.
Yeah, Thanks a lot, we've been really
enjoying this class. And we'll try and get
in touch and do another one of these later
in the course.