Let's talk about Kneser Ney Smoothing, one
of the most sophisticated forms of smoothing,
but also one with a beautiful
and elegant, intuition. Remember that from
good touring, we talked about the c stars,
the discounted counts you end up from good
touring and we discounted each of the
counts, the count of one was discounted to
point four, and the count of two
discounted to 1.26 and so on, in order to
save mass to replace the zero counts with
some low number. And if you look at the
actual values of these counts, 8.25 for
nine and 7.24 for eight, you'll notice
that in a very large number of cases.
[sound]. The discounted count has a very
close relationship, with the original
count. It's really the original count
minus 0.75, or somewhere close to that.
So. In practice what good touring often
does is produce a fixed small discount
from the count. And that intuition, that,
of a fixed small discount can be applied
directly. When we do this, we call this
absolute discounting, and absolute
discounting is a popular kind of
smoothing. And here we're showing you
absolute discounting interpolation. And
again, the intuition is just we'll save
some time and have to compute all those
complicated good touring numbers and we'll
just subtract.75, or maybe it will be a
different discount value for different
corpora. Now here's the equation for
absolute discounting. So we, we're doing
diagrams again. So the probability.
Absolute discounted of a word, given the
previous word, will be some discounted
bigram interpolated, with some
interpolation weight, with the unigram
probability. So we have a unigram
probability PFW, and then the bigram
probability, and we just subtract a fixed
amount. Let's say it's.75 from the count.
And otherwise, compute the bigram
probability in the normal way. So, we have
a discounted bigram probability, mixed
with some weight, which I'll talk later
about how to set this weight, with a
unigram. And, maybe, we might keep a
couple extra values of D for accounts one
and two. Accounts one and two on a
previous slide weren't quite subtracting
point seven five, so we can model this
more carefully by having separate counts
for those. But the problem with absolute
discounting is the unigram probability
itself. And I want to talk about changing
the unigram probability. And that's the
fundamental intuition of Kneser-Ney. So in
Kneser-Ney smoothing, the idea is keep
that same interpolation that we saw in
absolute discounting, but use a better
estimate of probabilities of the lower
unigrams. And the intuition for that, we
can go back and look at the classic
Shannon games. Remember, in the Shannon
game we're predicting a word from previous
words, so we see a, a sentence, I can't
see without my reading. What's the most
likely next word? Well, glasses seems
pretty likely. Well, how about instead the
word Francisco? Well, that seems very
unlikely in this situation and yet,
Francisco as just a unigram is more common
than glasses. But the reason why Francisco
seems like a bad thing after reading, one
intuition we might be able to get is that
Francisco always follows San or very often
follows San. So while Francisco is very
frequent, it's frequent in the context of
the word San. Now, unigrams in an
interpellation model, where we're mixing a
unigram and a bigram, are specifically
useful, they're, they're very helpful just
in case where we haven't seen a bigram. So
it's unfortunate that just in the case
where we haven't seen a bigram, reading
Francesco, we're trusting Francesco's
unigram weight which is just where we
should trust him. So instead of using the
probability of W, how likely is a word,
our intuition is going to be when we're
backing off to something we should instead
use the continuation probability. We're
going to call it P continuation of a word.
How likely is the word to appear as a
novel continuation? Well, how do we
measure novel continuation? Well, for each
word we'll just count the number of bigram
types it completes. How many different
bigrams does it, does it create by
appearing after another word. In other
words, each bigram type is a novel
continuation the first time we see this
new bigram. In other words, the
continuation probability. Is gonna be
proportional to, the Cardinality of this
set. The number of words of, of preceding
words, I minus one, that occur with our
word. So, how many, whats, how many words,
occur, before this word in a Bi-gram. How
many preceding words are there. That will
be, that, that [inaudible], the
Cardinality of that set, that's a number
we would like our continuation
probability, to be proportional to. So how
many times does W appear as a [inaudible]
continuation? We need to turn that into a
probability. So we just divide by the
total number of word bi-gram types. So, of
all word bi-grams. Them, that occur, more
than zero times, what's the cardinal event
set? How many different word by gram types
are there, and we're just going to divide
the two, to get a probability of
continuation, of all the number of word by
gram types how many of those have W as a
novel continuation? Now it turns out that
there's an alternative metaphor for the
same equations so again we can see the
numerator as the number, the total number
of word types that precede W, how many
word types can W follow And we're gonna
normalize it by the number of words that
could precede all words. So, this sum over
all words of, the, then, number of word
types that can precede the word. And these
two are the same. The number of this
denominator and the denominator we saw on
the previous slide are the same because
the number of possible biogram types is
the same as the number of word type that
can precede all word [inaudible] over
words. If you think about it for a second,
you'll realize that true. So in other
words with this kind of Kneser nine a
frequent word like Francisco that occurs
only in one context like San will have a
low continuation probability. So if we put
together, the intuition of absolute
discounting with the Kneser-Ney
probability for the lower order Ingram, we
have the Kneser-Ney smoothing algorithm.
So, For the bigram itself we just have
absolute discounting. We take the, the
bigram count. We subtract some d discount.
And I've just shown here that we take the
max of that n0 because, obviously, if the
discount happens to be higher than the
probability we don't want a negative
probability. And we're just gonna
interpret like that with this same
continuation probability that we just saw,
p continuation of w sub i. And, the
lambda, now let's talk about how to
compute that lambda. The lambda is gonna
take all that probability mass from all
those, all those normalized discounts that
we took out of these higher-order
probabilities, and w-, use those to, to,
to, to weight, how much probability we
should assign to the unigram. We're gonna
combine those. So that lambda is the, the
amount of the discount weight divided by
the, the, the denominator, there. So, it's
the normalized discount. And then, we're
gonna multiply that by the total number of
word types can follow this context, WI
minus one. In other words, how many
different word types? Did we discount or
how many times did we apply this
normalized discount? And we multiply those
together and we get, we know how much
probably mass total we can, now, assign to
the continuation of the worm. Now, this is
the bigram formulation for [inaudible].
Now in this slide, we're showing you the
general recursive formulation for engrams
in general, and here we have to make a
slight change to, To deal with all the
high-order n-grams. So here we're just
showing the Kneser-Ney probability of a
word, given the prefix of the word. And,
just like Kneser-Ney we saw before, we're
just interpolating a bi, a, a high-order
n-gram which is discounted with, with a, a
lambda weight and a lower-order
probability. But now we need to
distinguish between the very first. Top
level time that we use a count and these
lower order, counts. So we're going to use
the actual count for the very high if
order bi-gram, and we're going to use the
continuation value that we, just defined
earlier for all the lower order
probabilities. So we'll define this new
thing count kinase [inaudible] of dot
which will mean actual count. This will be
actual count, let's say we're doing
trigrams for the trigram. And then when we
recurse and have the,
the Kneser-Ney probability for the lower
order things when we get down to the
bi-grams and uni-grams, we'll be using the
continuation count that's again the, the,
the single word context that we defined
earlier. So Kneser-Ney smoothing,
a very excellent algorithm. It's very
commonly used in speech recognition and
machine translation and yet it has a very
beautiful and elegant intuition and I hope
you appreciate it.