I'd like to follow-up on our last lecture
about the sociological imagination and
talk about three questions that are
characteristic of the discipline of
sociology, and the first is: How are the
things that we take to be natural socially
constructed? How are the things that we
take to be natural socially constructed?
There's a basic flaw in common sense, and
human reasoning more generally, that goes
something like this. The things we see
before us every day are supposed to be
that way, they come from nature But
sociology teaches us, that Many of the
things that we, think are natural Are
actually man and woman made, Which does
not necessarily mean this makes us, freer
from so called nature. In fact, we may not
be As free as we think, even armed with
this insight But that hasn't stopped many
people from using the inside to try to
bring about very important social changes.
Some of which have succeeded and some of
which, are slow to progress For example,
let's say that you go up to a baby or a
small child on the street, at least here
in Princeton, New Jersey, Perhaps in a
stroller or crawling next to the parents.
What's the first question you're going to
ask those parents? Very likely you're
gonna say, "Does your child have a penis
or a vagina?" You need to know the answer
to that question right? Because without
knowing the answer to that question you
cannot precede any further in the
interaction. That is if you are a typical
human being like me And this is because
without knowing if the child has a penis
or a vagina you don't really know how to
interact with that child. Now in fact,
it's probably not the best thing in the
world to ask that question in that way to
a parent. In fact, if you were to go up
and ask the question in that way, at least
here in Princeton and all of the other
places where I have lived, you would be
considered very unusual, if not strange.
So instead, we ask the question in a more
benign way. We say is your child a boy, or
a girl. Well, actually, even if you ask it
like that, some parents will not be
thrilled because they want to believe that
you can tell what their child is. Which
highlights how significant it is that we
be able to interact with a child in an
appropriate way So when you go up to a
child on the street, the first thing you
might say to a parent is; what's your
baby's name? That's a kind of subtle way
of asking the sex of the boy or the girl
without saying I can't really tell if your
child is a boy or a girl And once you
figure out whether or not you are
interacting with a boy or a girl, that
might cause some significant difference in
the way that you will in, interact, or
what you will say next. So if you find out
that it is a little boy named Michael,
which is a popular boy's name. When people
currently at Princeton were born in the
early'90s, you might say, hey buddy, how
are you doing? Or if you find out that
it's a little girl named Ashley, which was
also a popular girl's name in the
early'90s, when many of the students at
Princeton who are here today were born.
You might say, hi sweetie, how are you?
That will be the beginning of a kind of
interaction that is gender based. By
gender, we mean The social, cultural and
psychological meanings. Which get
attributed to sex And I'd be curious by
the way, about how this all works In the
places that you live. Why is gender so
important to social interaction? There's
nothing else quite like that. If we go up
to a baby on the street, and we don't know
what race they are, we can pretty well
interact with them, at least here in the
United States. Sure, there are parents who
will signal a certain racial affiliation
by how they fix the child's hair, or what
kind of garments they have the child wear,
but on the whole, people don't need to
know the race of a child in order to
interact with it. Whether the child is
black or white or Latino or Asian for
example, is not going to have a
significant impact on the nature of the
interaction. The same thing with social
class, right? We don't really need to know
what social class a child comes from in
ord er to interact with it. In order for
an interaction to be successful, we don't
need to know whether a child is from the
working classes or the middle classes or
the upper middle classes or that group
that has become popularly known as the top
one percent. There are many of the people
of the upper classes who dress their
children in clothes from the Gap or Old
Navy Stores which sell their products very
widely to people of many different classes
And likewise, there are many poor people
in the United States who dress their
children in labels that come from elite
names like Ralph Lauren or Tommy Hilfiger.
You can't necessarily tell what social
class a baby comes from And more
importantly, you don't feel you need to
know But gender is completely different.
You expect to know the gender of a child
before you can interact with it. Now the
one thing that occurs to you, or to me
when you need to know the gender of a
child and that all interactions are
gendered from the beginning is you come to
the realization that from a very early age
a child is going to be enacting the role
of a boy or a girl. They re gonna respond
to the expectations of the people around
them with regard to gender And through
processes of interaction, they are going
to come to think about themselves as a boy
or a girl And because this happens at such
a young age, when they're infants, in
fact. We can see the ways that gender
expectations come to be socially
constructed at the earliest part of life.
Now this is not to suggest that this thing
I am saying is social, does not have some
biological basis to it. This is not to
suggest that brain science does not have a
significant amount to contribute to our
understanding by looking at the
differences between male and female brains
But that what it does suggest is that
there is a very strong component of male
and female that is socially constructed.
Part of my agenda in this lecture is not
to say that the biological is a residual
category that doesn't matter, but to say
that we're going to engage in an enter
prise of disentangling. To try to figure
out which parts are biological, and which
are social because from the standpoint of
common sense, it is all biological. Most
people who are not educated in sociology
see these differences as rooted in nature.
A few years ago, the president of Harvard,
Larry Summers made a deliberately
provocative statement, for which he later
apologized, Suggesting that the existence
of fewer women in science might have
something to do with there being fewer
women at the higher end of the
intelligence distribution as measured by
IQ scores. He was trying to suggest that
there was something innate or natural
about this outcome. Now, once we know that
there is a strong social component to male
and female. We may hope that there are
things that we can do to influence the
environment that may actually have an
impact on the long term outcomes of men
and women. We know that there is
significant amount of gender inequality
even in the United States today A country
that has been thinking about these
differences longer than some other
countries. And at the same time we find
that many of these differences are
intractable, or very difficult to
eradicate. But to come back to the
statement by the president of Harvard,
there's actually been some progress in
getting more women into fields like
biological scientists. Summers' remarks
ignored some very important data. In 1966,
less than one percent of U.S. Doctoral
degrees in engineering were awarded to
women. While in 2001, the number had risen
to about seventeen%. Surely the IQ of
women at the high end of the distribution
didn't change. Not significantly during
this period. These numbers suggest that a
lot of progress still needs to be made.
Some of our institutions in American
society are working very hard to ask what
we can do to change gender inequality and
to change the sense of how it is natural
for man and women to behave or act in
particular ways. In math and science
training, a vast amount of sociological
research has demonstrated that when teach
ers or parents have low expectations for
girls then women will not develop their
potential talents. We know that for a very
long time in universities like Princeton
there were very few women who went into
science and engineering And it was a sense
on the part of many women who went into
these universities that is was a male
thing to do. This view is something that
was encouraged in the earliest stage of
life. Over time expectations have changed.
We have more and more women going into
science and engineering, but these are
things that the university knows begin
with a pipeline. They can only be changed
if the stereotypes and the sense of what
is appropriate and natural for different
genders to take on changes at the earliest
parts of life. Coinciding perhaps with the
very moment when we are starting to
interact with children in gendered ways or
let's take an even more controversial
example, racial differences in IQ.
Sometimes when white people find out that
I'm a sociologist they'll ask why it is
that blacks are doing worst than whites in
the United States And it's not uncommon
for folks to suggest to me that it is
because they're not as smart. And they'll
cite evidence that blacks have lower IQ
scores in general. Quote, they're not as
smart so they don't do as well, right? Now
it is true that blacks have lower IQ
scores In general, than whites in the
United States. People, who argue this,
argue that it's based on genetics. One
explanation is that they have smaller
brains than whites. But that is wrong. In
his book "Intelligence and how to get it,"
Richard Nesbitt says that Albert Einstein
had a smaller brain than the average black
person. Brain size is not the cause of
these differences. There's also the claim
that these lower IQ's are inherited. Well,
there are many studies that have been done
that have demonstrated. The ways that IQ,
is also based on the environmental
influences The social context, in which
people live. Thus, according to Nisbit,
the average child in a poor family will
hear substantially fewer words, per day,
then someone in an upper middle class
family. By a time a child reaches five
years old, he or she will hear many more
words in a higher income family.
Vocabulary, it turns out, is a very
significant determinant of how people do
on IQ tests. According to Nisbit, the
average IQ in the United States over the
course of the past 50 years since World
War [inaudible] has gone up fifteen to
twenty points. That is just the average
for Americans, as a whole And it's
impossible for the genetics of the country
to have changed that much over the past 50
years. So we know that there is something
about the environment of the United States
that is affecting the group as a whole And
during this period, the average difference
in IQ between blacks and whites decreased
significantly. It was fifteen points in
1945 and its nine points today. According
to Nisbit, that corresponds to a certain
level of improvement in the black
population, compared to the white
population, in their standard of living.
The average lack today has a higher IQ
than the average white in 1950, another
interesting thing to explain. So these are
some examples of how it is that one of the
great achievements of the social sciences
and thinking about IQ has been to
understand the way that many things we
take to be natural are not completely
based on genetics but are themselves a
function of the social environment