Greetings everyone and welcome to the
first session, our first live session of
Introduction to Sociology. The last few
days have been simply extraordinary in
terms of the response and the discussion,
on the course website which I've been
following. Although I have not been able
to respond, to each and everyone of your
postings, I want you to know that I've
been looking carefully at the many things
that you have written and I am so
impressed with the level and quality of
the discussion and the ways in which you
are all helping one another along to
develop a better understanding of the
material. This is peer learning at its
best and this a very impressive group of
students from all over the world. I want
to begin today by thanking my own
administration. The President and the
provost, and the Dean of the faculty and
the Dean of the college, and the Associate
Dean, and the people at the McGraw
Teaching Center, and the people working
here in the broadcast center at Princeton
University for making all of this
possible. It's this university's
commitment to bringing courses like this
to a wider public and being inclusive that
has made this possible and their decision
to devote the resources to this kind of
enterprise makes, me feel wonderful as a
member of the Princeton faculty and I know
that my colleagues on the Princeton
faculty feel as though very similarly to
me that this is a very special moment in
the history of higher education that we
are a part of, that we have the privilege
of being a part of. And, I want to say
also that, you know, this is really part
of a pretty long standing tradition here
at Princeton. In our university we have a
very generous financial aide package to
students who come here from a very wide
variety of backgrounds. And one of the
things that I think didn't come across in
the article by Malcolm Gladwell is the
extent to which that is significant on the
ongoing life of Princeton. We have
certainly the best financial aid package
in the world and it is something that we
ar e very proud of. Probably 60 percent of
our students are on financial aid. Our
students are not required to take out
loans to come here. The financial aid is
available to students not only from the
United States but from all over the world.
And that extends to $5,000 to $50,000
depending on the needs of an individual
family in a given year and I have received
questions over e-mail for students around
the world asking whether or not, it's
possible for people from outside the
United States to apply for financially
aid. And the answer is yes, there are no
limitations on that and financial need is
not taking into consideration when
admissions decisions are made. Over ten
percent of our student body comes from
outside the United States and many of
those students are on financial aid. I
want to talk today about the Malcolm
Gladwell article but first I want to begin
by discussing in some detail. The article
that we read by C. Wright Mills which was
written of course in 1959. And I want to
begin by welcoming the students from
around the world who are part of our
seminar for today. I should say at the
outset that we invited a couple of more
people to join us today and for technical
reasons, some of them are not up on the
screen, they might pop up during the
course of our conversation. But for the
time being, we are going to speak with the
people that are there. I'd like them to
introduce themselves to us beginning with
the person on the far left, Dipendra. And
then let's go to each person and I'd like
the each of you to say something about
what you thought was most interesting,
something brief about what you thought was
most interesting about Mills's essay, The
promise. Dipendra. >> Hi, this is Di,
Nepal. And if you are wondering where
Nepal is we are in, India, a small
country, country. I come from, my
bachelors in rural development and I have
a major in sociology as well. Particular
interested in, in this, today's lecture by
C. Wright Mills. I've been very much
fascinated for those examples of study
relating to the institution of the society
specifically at his out during the lecture
regarding divorce and marriage. That was
one thing very much interesting to me.
Another thing we tried, the last, the text
which is that if you want to develop your
socialism then you should plays very, mean
. So, that, about the thing that have been
striking ... >> Okay. Dipendra
unfortunately the connection to you was
not great and but I will summarize though
that you thought that the, one of the most
interesting things has to do with the
connection of the sociological imagination
to marriage and divorce. And, we will look
forward to hearing more from you later
hopefully with a better connection. Doug?
>> Yeah, hi. I'm Doug, I'm from
Philadelphia. I, I don't know. I, The
Promise I believe is the name of the
paper. My impression, it was really hard
to understand you know, trying to put
myself back in 1959 and trying to
understand where it was coming from. It
seemed almost like you're just trying to
focus on the psychology I guess of being
trapped. But I also want, I, I did
understand the basic thing of where I was
going with it. >> Doug, could you tell us
a little bit about yourself in
Philadelphia. >> Yeah, I'm a firefighter
in Philadelphia. 34 years old which I
think makes me the oldest member of the
panel. I you know, I took a little bit of
college. After high school I was in the
Navy most of the time. And now I'm trying
to get back in college. >> And are you,
are you talking to us from the firehouse
right now? >> No. No, I can't. >> [laugh]
>> I can't do that. [laugh] . >> [laugh]
>> All that I say is what my opinion, it
has nothing to do with the Fire
Department. But no, I'm at my house and
yeah, I'm excited to hear. >> Okay. Thank
you, Doug. >> My name is Estela Diaz. I'm
a Princeton University student majoring in
Sociology. I'm originally from Los
Angeles, California and currently livin g
in Spanish Harlem in New York City. One of
the things I thought was most interesting
is considering the sociological
imagination in context of the United
States 2012 political campaign and the
presidential election. I'm just kind of
considering how issues are framed. Whether
they are framed as, personal issues or
public issues specially the economic
downturn. >> Fascinating. Is it Nana who's
next? >> I'm Nana. I'm from Georgia. It's
Caucasus not Georgia in USA. >> [laugh].
>> I am working as a representative of
Israeli delegation here in Georgia and
Ukraine and in Belarus. Also I have a
travel company with my friend. We're
dealing with the incoming tourists and for
me the most I pay attention on the
sociological imagination check through
one, it was quite interesting for me how
people can imagine the scenes in word and
also marriage and divorce because in
Georgia it's quite complicated. >> Thank
you, Nana. And then finally. >> Hello, my
name is [inaudible] University School of
[inaudible] and National Relations which
is the case in Southwestern Russia. I
found this article very interesting
because it's effect that's a lot just a
moment in terms of historical change and
even the so we have to, to think more, to
think wider in this case. >> That's very
interesting. Okay, well, these are some
very interesting ways of beginning our
thinking about what Mills was trying to
say and what I'd like to do now with you
guys is to try to go through the essay in
a little bit of detail from Kathmandu, to
Siberia, to Georgia, to Spanish Harlem, to
Philadelphia and talk about the meaning of
some of these lines and how we should
interpret them. I want to begin with the
first paragraph, the second line where
Mills says, they sensed that within their
everyday world, they cannot overcome their
troubles and this feel, and this feeling
they are quite often correct. One question
that I want to ask you is this, is, is
there some sense in which t hat line and
the essay as a whole gives the impression,
gives an impression to people that if only
they can develop a sociological
imagination, that they can overcome their
troubles. And is that really realistic?
What are some of the dilemmas involved in
thinking about this in such a way? >>
Yeah. I believe that was something that
had, something to do a little bit more of
this psychology of it you know, somebody
that's kinda trapped in their own.
Sometimes made up show is because they
feel, I mean it's almost like looking at
this you know, I was never able, I wasn't
much of a person that was very come out in
high school I guess so I didn't take the
college route. And when as I got older, I
wanted to go to college but now this is
forwarding opportunity. I feel like I'm
widening now a little bit like from
personal experience so that's kinda like
the way I look at it like. Instead of me
sentencing that within my own shell, now I
feel like I'm just through this course.
I'm feeling like I'm kind of getting over
it. >> And, and is there a sense though I,
I, I'm curious to know in which, does
having a sociological imagination give us
any legitimate reason to believe that we
are in a better position to overcome our
personal troubles? Or is that, is that an
unrealistic kind of thing to begin, to
begin the essay with? >> I didn't
personally interpret it as such instead I
interpreted this repeated notion of not
being able to overcome one's personal
troubles. I interpreted that as Mills is
arguing for a larger perspective not
necessarily saying that having a
sociological imagination will allow you to
overcome troubles but instead emphasizing
that our troubles are not strictly derived
from the individual. So Mills is arguing
that having sociological imagination will
give you a different perspective on your
troubles but it will not necessarily solve
your troubles. >> Very interesting. Would
anyone else like to comment on this? >> I
think almost the same because I, I think
it's not d epend to overcome troubles.
It's, it's not coming from the
sociological imagination, you can you can
solve your troubles and solve your
problems without knowing it but it helps
you quite a lot. >> And, but are you sure
about that, Norma? Are you really sure
that having the sociological imagination
would help you in solving the personal
troubles? >> No. Like in your day dream.
>> Oh, really? Could you say more about
that? >> Like say in Georgia if, if you're
like for people who are coming from
abroad, it's, it's not easy to find some
jobs. If you are not an investor it's not
easy to find it. If you know the
sociological imagination like to help the,
the, help people, how people think about
it, you will not come in Georgia and start
your work here. You will go to another
country to find some job. Let's say, let's
say this example. >> So, in other words,
having the socio, that's a really good
answer. Having the sociological
imagination is going to perhaps one way of
having a sociological imagination is to
know our probabilities and understanding
the probabilities means that we can access
our chances and decide what we should try
and what we shouldn't try, right? >> Yeah.
>> Okay. But let me ask you a question
Estela. You're a Princeton student, okay?
>> If you knew. >> Mm-hm. >> The
probabilities when you applied to
Princeton, of being accepted, would you
have ever tried? >> I mean, I think kind
of did know the probabilities with less
than ten percent acceptance rate. And
over, I think it's, it was about 30,000
people who applied, higher, with only,
with less than 2,000 of us being accepted,
the probability was extremely low. But you
have to, in, in case, in the case of
applying to Princeton University, I think
there was something worth a lot more than,
I think it was worth taking my chances. >>
But the thing is, is just, did having a
sociological imagination and knowing the
odds, did that increases the chance of you
applying or don't you think that there are
some people w ho are having that knowledge
might have said, it's not worth it to try
at all. I mean, if somebody to finds out
that, that the chances of, the chances of
doing, of succeeding in any fields are
small, does that knowledge necessarily
help them in the end? We assume, we're,
we're assuming that it's empowering to
have that knowledge but I wonder if it
could also be disempowering. >> I think I
could. >> Go ahead. >> It could certainly
be discouraging specially if you consider
Mills article in general, he's kind of
taking away from the notion of individual
agency and individual power. So when you
take that away, it does and can seem very
discouraging. >> Doug, what do you think
about this? >> Well, basically I, I think
that Estela could nail it on the head. The
you know, that sense of you know, when
like things are hopeless, people are going
to say, why am I gonna put the effort in?
But, if you realize like Estela did that
you know, that doesn't just define who you
are that, that you know, that ten%, if
you're going to borrow that ten%, you're
part of that ten percent like what are you
going to do about it? It is what it is and
that really, I think that could really be
freeing for somebody because that's not
going to really upset them if they turn
around and get rejected. They'll say,
okay, whatever, you know, although I was
ready for that. It's kinda like a you
know, expect the, expect the worst or hope
for the best and expect the worst kind of
thing, I guess. And I don't know if I am
missing that point. >> Let's move on to
the next to the next part of the paper. At
the very beginning of the second
paragraph, Mills says, underlying the
sense of being trapped are seemingly
impersonal changes the very structure of
continent wide societies. There were some
discussion on the discussion boards over
the last few days about what Mills meant
by impersonal changes. And I thought that
you guys did a very good job of clarifying
the issue for those who were confused but,
what does this mean to you? What are some
of the kinds of impersonal changes that
affect you in the society in which you
live as a way of conceiving of what Mills
is talking about. Dipendra, could you
start? >> In, in, I was very much
interested in the previous paragraph so I
was about to speak but I lost my
connection. So, maybe I would rather go
back to that paragraph and I'll resume to
this paragraph at the end. >> Sure, why
don't you do that. >> So, in the previous
thing. >> Go ahead, please do. >> So, I
have a different I have a, I have a
different perspective on that it does say,
it is said that within the everyday works
they cannot overcome the troubles. I want
to keep myself in this example. I have my
parents divorced. So in this actually when
my parents, then was suddenly, the problem
that I'm facing in the world. So, I,
believe is facing this kind of problem and
I was so I have a small sister and I have
my mom crying in front of me everyday and
my dad, dad was with another woman. So,
how I felt, it was like I felt that this
was only me. This is only, I'm the guy
problem. But sociological imagination, I
think that in a broader perspective, when
I look at my society then I see a lot of
people who get who get divorced so then,
then I do is, I simply hiding myself and
say that, okay boy, this is, this is not
only the way you move ahead. It's not,
spend your whole life regretting because
your dad married to another woman or
something. So, where, and I look at only
when I think back is my problem only and I
feel I'm trapped in that problem. But when
I come out of my family, when I come out,
when I look at my society then I feel a
lot, this is the broader perspective that
I should look into and that, that is, that
really motivated me. >> Well, I think
that, that is a really wonderful statement
because what you're saying is that you
feel as though the understanding that your
experience was not a personal problem but
was part of a larger trend and a larger
public issue inspired you to feel
empowered. And that you decided that you
are going to rise above your social
circumstances with that knowledge knowing
that was not your fault or knowing that
this was not the fault of your, your
family and I actually, I think that's a
really excellent response to my concern
and it's, it's really a nice response
because I think that in the case of
divorce, it's true that many children feel
as though they are themselves the cause of
their parents divorce so they feel as
though they are responsible for it and
certainly it's true that the family
members blame themselves and I think it's,
it is the case that if you know that
you're part of something larger and wider,
perhaps that is actually empowering. To be
able to get beyond it and move beyond it.
And yet I must tell you that I feel still
nevertheless a certain concern over these
lines and what they imply in the essay
because for many people, you know, their
lives are just really hard. And, it is
going to be hard for them whether they
know that they're part of a larger social
trend or not. And the ability to rise
beyond their social, social circumstances,
I worry takes a lot more obviously than
any kind of knowledge or understanding of
this kind but perhaps that's just, that's
just obvious and not worth being overly,
overly concerned with. By the way in our
Princeton Seminars, there are moments as
Estela will tell you, of complete silence.
And I encourage those moments in my
seminar I believe in silence. I think it's
great for people to be able to sit and
think for a second. Sometimes we'll have
silence for 30 seconds in the room before
somebody talks. We shouldn't always feel
pressure to fill in every gap at every
moment and no more so just because we
happen to be on the Internet for 30,000
other students right now. Does anybody
else have anything they wanted to add to
that before we move on there, then. >>
Yes. May I add something. It will be kind
of question. Wh en, when you are talking
in your lecture about sociological
imagination, we find that marriage and
divorce, situations and issues, I remember
the words of Soviets secrets General
Joseph Stalin cuz he once said to Averill
Harriman he said, the death if one man is
a tragedy, the death of million is
statistic. I'd like to know the terminals
of General Joseph Stalin and happen he was
a dictator. That was just the first thing
that came to my mind. Whether there is an
argument whether he said it or not. So I
wanted to ask a bit political question. He
said that in terms of historical change
has also Mills noted. Our lives are only a
moment so today anything around us could
be revealed as statistic even our lives
can be statistic within this cope of the
population size and then the scope of many
other issues. So our president tells about
radius. When he tells about radius, he
sites average which is data. Why doesn't
he site the lowest, for example Tatiana
who is which a school teacher in Siberia
in who has four children and tries to
survive the four kids. How do you think
professor? Can the government treat its
people just as a statistic? And where is
the border of statistic and the real life?
>> Well, I think that it's very tempting
to use a single statistic and of course
what a sociological imagination is going
to do, is going to try to encourage people
to look at the variation. And to try to
explain the variation in a society. And, I
think that there's always a tendency to
try to put the focus in one place or the
other but your job is as the sociologist
is to move toward and understanding and
grasping of that variation in which you
just did in your wonderful comment and
that's a great quote which I'm sure that
I'll be using in the future when I give
this lecture again. I want to ask you guys
to take a peek though at the notion of
that first line in the essay and I want to
get back to this issue of impersonal
changes. Could you guys try to think about
what that means and try to help the
students who were concerned about that all
on the website to reflect on that a little
bit more. What are some of the impersonal
changes in, in your society? Nana has gone
off, why do we go to Doug? >> When I look
at these line as far as impersonal
changes, I felt like that was something
that, you know, in an, in an, in a time, I
mean, it was brought up before about
what's going on with the housing crisis,
with the job crisis and everything else.
And at the time when jobs are, you know,
so you know, far between, somebody can
very easily think for themselves whether
there's something wrong with me that's why
I'm not working. Then, if they look at
the, you know, the way that everything is
in the society, it's not a, it's not a
personal change that you need to make it's
the way that the society is that, you
know, that the, the structure and as it
go, the very structure of the kind of wide
society that if there's, there's change
made to the system you know, not something
that has to do with this one person like I
feel like that line is trying to give
somebody a little bit of hope you know,
like look it's not you, you have the
ability, you just need to understand it.
If there's a problem out there right now,
I think we're just going to need to try a
little bit harder and don't let yourself
down and don't feel like you're trapped.
>> Okay. Estela? >> No, I think he saw
that very well. I'm trying to think. I'm
looking at what he says the structure of
continent wide societies and just
contextualizing this in nineteen, I mean,
if we consider the effect of the Internet
now in our very discussion here today, we
were discussing that's what people on
various continent and greatest countries.
So looking at impersonal changes that's
something far beyond our, what he says as
personal, personal troubles. >> Yeah. I
think that one of the things that, that
concerns me about this point as well is
that, you know, the emphasis on obviously
the impersonal changes and that as if they
are always trapping us. And I think that
we have to have more neurons to view of it
at least I would propose that and the you
know, you know, the impersonal change of
today, today of the Internet obviously is
also leading to possibilities like the one
that we have before us right now. And, I
think that our job as a sociologist is to
look at the ways in which impersonal
changes not only trap us, but also
liberate us and potentially make us more
free. And I wonder whether or not anybody
could present an example other than the
Internet of any kind of impersonal change
in their own society. Or perhaps the
internet is the best one for your society
right now that you'd like to refer to.
But, in which the actual impersonal change
has been liberating rather than simply
constraining. Remember silence is fine.
Silence is good in the seminar. Everyone
can think. >> I think that was a good
example, try to recover other issues. >>
Okay. Well maybe we can ask our online
viewers. The other members of the class to
think about that issue a little bit as we
move forward in the class. I want to move
on now to a discussion of the New Yorker
article that was written by the great
writer the great non-fiction writer,
Malcolm Gladwell. And I, I saw some
questions on the discussion boards about
why I would have assigned this article for
the first class. And in fact, the article
was assigned for exactly the reason that
many of you proposed in your answers to
the person who asked that question because
I believe it exemplifies the sociological
imagination. Can you guys hear me right
now? Yes? Okay, good. So, let's begin now
by talking a little bit about Gladwell's
article. Gladwell being a Canadian who
came to the United States and was kind of
intrigued by the culture of New York City
in which he found that there were many p
eople who are obsessed with Harvard in
particular and the, and who seemed to
think that if they had gone there that
there was nothing greater, of greater
importance that could have happened to
them in their, in their lives. And he
wrote this essay based on the, as we know,
based on the research of sociologist
Jerome Karabel largely about the, the,
the, the, the nature of admissions at, at
Harvard, Princeton and Yale and the way in
which it moved in the direction that it is
in today. And, one of the things that I
found very interesting about the responses
on the Internet to this was that, there
were many people who saw the, the decision
of the Ivy League Schools to look at the
whole person rather than a single
dimension as meaning, as implying that,
that, that was somehow a false promise of
that they, or that, that, that people who
have been excluded that people, that they
themselves were being promised something
that wasn't really fair or obtainable when
they were giving the, the, the hope that
they one day could achieve or go to an Ivy
League School. And I'm just curious about
that response because my own feeling about
it in looking at the way that the system
of college admissions emerged is that
well, I think it's good that the largest
group of students in the university has
gotten there because of their academic
achievement. I think that it is also true
that there are so many other qualities in
life that make for a deserving and an
interesting human being. And, would we
really want a college to only include the
people who have the highest scores rather
than a system like the ones, the one that
has been designed which actually looks at
a much wider variety of personal
characteristics. And I'm just curious
about what your response was to some of
those comments and how you would design a
system like this if it was to you?
Dipendra. >> Actually when I was going
through this lecture, what I've heard was
the education system the admission system
that was there and unfortunately, in
Nepal, I've been practicing that now. So,
we have the, actually a brief background
of the, the admission system that we have
here and then I'll, I'll get back to my
point. So, here at Nepal, what was there
are typically two different kinds of
colleges or universities. The [inaudible]
all the university and all the college
here in Nepal is you should get at least
good master. At least, [inaudible] more
than 60 percent or more than three GPA so
that you can get into good college or
something like that. And very few very few
colleges and universities we have in hands
or fingers that they look overall student
or they look at overall characteristics of
students. So it would depend, but I would
like to say seeing, look at examples that
I have seen here in Nepal, what I have
come to conclude is typically, there are
two different university here that I would
like to mention in Nepal. The Tribhuvan
University which is government owned
university and Kathmandu University that
is privately owned university. So, why
does Tribhuvan University does? They don't
have a proper definite system of being in
students. So, every time they have it,
they get admission in that college. They
have let's say you have grossed 50 percent
then you'll get into that university and
where I am now. And before, before coming
to this university, I actually drop the
Kathmandu University because private
university and the, which required regal
competition. They had they had added a
baseline for academics. We need to get at
least 60 percent in your high school then
you, you should be astounding in extra
curricular activities, you should be
astounding in sports, you should be social
and so, so many characteristics. And
where, where the products that come out
after, in the universities after four
years, we can see a clear distinction here
in Nepal. Kathmandu University which have,
which have the syste m of looking student
from all dimension, the, the students are,
are, they are very practical then a lot of
them, you know, they are outgoing and
while we look at the students of Tribhuvan
University, what I see is students are
very much confined to books or not in, not
even in textbooks, we have just papers
here. That means the questions that, the
exams. So there are some predicted
questions and you go through that question
and you won't get questions out of that.
It is, sometimes that's really a very
difficult Tribhuvan University. So, what I
did is college student to get some
academics would be one of the primary
criteria. But we should have salute
students in overall how good they meddle
in society. How a good in this course. >>
Thank you. Thank you for that interesting
comment, Dipendra. Would anyone else like
to comment on this? >> Yes, may I comment.
>> Yes. >> Because getting in is a very
present problem for me and now I'm
graduating in a few days and then I'll be
I have to find educate masters program.
And while I was reading, getting in
article, I, I have a feeling you know,
well, the situation that existed in the
beginning of the twentieth Century in
Harvard University and Yale etc. With
standardized this now exists in Russia, in
the twenty-first Century, in the beginning
of twenty-first Century. So, I think it's
not a good way to admit students just on
the basis of standardized tests. Academic
records is a very is, is an important
problem but, but while admitting they
should see they should see the person
hopeless and hopeless and hope, he's
begral, he's experienced. What he can do
maybe just melt on the, his studies. >>
So, it's interesting to hear your
perspectives on this and it is true that
outside the United States that the
standards are usually much more narrow for
admissions decisions. And I think that,
that is what accounted for some of the
surprise that initially came on to the
site about the way that it's done here in
the United States. I want to, oh, I see we
have another person that just joined us.
Another Princeton student named Dickson
Lee. Hi, Dickson. >> Hi, Mitch. >> So,
we're talking right now about the Malcolm
Gladwell essay and one of the interesting
points that I want to sort of end by
thinking about, is something that came up
a lot on the discussion boards which was
the study that was cited and this is for
everybody, not just for Dickson. The study
that was cited by Gladwell, by my
colleague Alan Krueger, who did a study of
the people who were let's say,
hypothetically, as it's described in the
article, accepted into a state university
like Penn State, at a private university
like the University of Pennsylvania. And
what was his point in making that
comparison and what did he find. Does
anybody remember? It certainly listed on a
lot of response on the, the discussion
board. So they referred to it as comparing
apples to apples. And what they discovered
is that both, both the person who decides
to go to more elite university, "elites",
and the person who decides to go to state
school, both do well in the future. With
the finding of one exemption which is
those from the lowest economic strata.
Those from this strata were seen as
benefiting from the elite's education. And
it didn't say, it didn't explained this in
anyway but that was the finding. >> Can
anybody explain, thank you Estela. Can
anybody explain to us what was the logic
of the article. He used the word selection
and treatment and what was the exact way
in which he went about doing study in
which those words became so important.
What was he measuring? What was he
comparing? Does anybody have any memory of
that aspect of the article? What was
Krueger doing there? In the traditional,
it's just to jog your memory, in the
traditional measures of the impact of an
Ivy League educati on, comparisons have
been made between the salaries of people
who graduated from Ivy League Schools and
the salaries of people who graduated from
other schools and what Kruger said was,
let's change the comparison. Instead of
comparing it in that way, how did we do
it? He compared the people who were the
same person. He only took people who were
graduated, who admitted both to private
schools, to Ivy League Schools and to
other schools and who chose for some
reason, to go to the other school instead.
And he compared those same people against
the average people who came out of Ivy
League Schools and he found out that those
people actually did just as well as the
people who went to Ivy League Schools. And
so his point was, that it was not
necessarily the treatment of going to an
Ivy League School that matter, in terms of
the success of people but it was instead
the, the, the selection into the system
from the very beginning of certain kinds
of people that were destined to be
successful. And he basically, despite the
fact that he's a Princeton professor and
have, has every reason to be biased in
favor of the Ivy League, he concluded that
the impact of the Ivy League is not nearly
as great as it's taken to be by the wider
society and the wider world. Now it seems
to me that kind of analysis that Krueger
did, is in the best tradition of the
sociological imagination. And it seems to
me that, that kind of information should
be empowering to many people regardless of
whether or not they would even want to
come to Princeton or some other Ivy League
School. Did you guys did that, did that
information make a similar impression on
you guys? What effect did it have on you
to read that part of the article? >> Yeah,
it's understood. Yeah, I understand what
you're saying. The, the, the one, the one
quote that he has here is having pen on
your resume opens doors. And I do notice
that there is that sort of the meanest
attitude when it comes to society in
general. People turn and mayb e look at
certain people or certain kind of way and
to put them up on the pedestal and you
know, it can sometimes be a little
unfortunate that they would do something
like that but you know, I understand and
because there's such an emphasis that's
been put on for so long about who's coming
out where just you know, how, also like
what he said earlier in the article you
know when he, when somebody said they were
from Harvard it was like everybody in the
room got quiet you know and they were
like, oh, this guy is from Harvard. Just
like I understand that's what he's, that's
what he was explaining. And it kind of
seems to me like, I'm not sure if I got
the right, what you were saying was that
some, some of this, well, did really well
in the lower tier school like the they
thought the, the state school, that they
only did as good as the people who are
like average students in the Ivy League
School. >> No, no, no, no. It was exactly
the opposite of that. He is basically
saying that if you took the same person
who is admitted to both, then it's really
ultimately the individual who mattered
more than. >> Okay. >> The social, the
social context. >> Okay, so, yes. I, I
just, I understood that he was talking
about that, that having, you know, having
pen on your resume, that's basically, you
know, the whole, the, the general thing
basically. Your dream is what you're
looking at. You know, when you're coming
out of that school, you're grand and
people look at that and they think that
when you're coming out of Penn or Harvard,
you're like a Mercedes. >> Right. But his.
>> When you're coming out of Penn State.
>> But his point though is, and it's
important to clarify this and make sure
that we get on the same page on this point
is that his point is that when you look at
the statistical data , for large numbers
of people then, those anecdotal stories
actually don't have as much explanatory
value as the analysis that he did would
have. Dickson, what do you think about
this? >> So, when I was reading over i t,
I was interested to see that he says that
person who is accepted to Penn and the
person whose accepted to Penn State would
do the same thing but then I was
wondering, so admissions factors don't
always account for everything that person
is capable of. So, I think it might have
just outside of the scope for its project.
But I think that I would have been
interested at project have continued and
then look at. So what are the things that
the, students for and how those affect
people in the upper strata that normally
wouldn't be affected by the treatment that
Princeton gives than, like the, really
lower, lower strata that I was talking
about earlier. >> I think that's very
interesting. So, basically, I hope that we
can use Alan Krueger's study as a way of
getting of thinking more about the
questions that I raised at the end of the
first lecture of how it is that the
individual makes a difference? And the
extent to which we are truly trapped by
certain social circumstances. Sometimes,
we imagine that the social circumstances
that are surrounding us, are trapping us
in ways that they actually are not and it
takes constant sociological investigation
to know the difference between a real trap
and an illusion of one. So, I want to end
today's discussion by just saying a little
bit about where we're going next. I want
to say, first of all, that this was an
experiment today. I, I know that the
discussion was by no means perfect
although it was as good as I could have
ever hoped from a group of students around
the world and I thought that your comments
on the, in the seminar today were really
great and interesting and a wonderful
beginning. But technically it could be
improved and we will certainly work on
that in the weeks to come. I really
appreciate the patience of everybody whose
watching as well as your interest and I
appreciate your support and your
understanding that we are part now of a
really big experiment. We're trying to do
something new and I suspect that we're
going t o learn a lot along the way. When
we meet the next time in the online forum,
we're going to include some new people
that were not here today. We'll also have
some familiar faces. We'll try to
substitute some new people in to keep the
conversation representing different parts
of the world. And, we will try to do some
things to improve it each time until we
really get to a point where it is
something that is working really well and
we are really happy with it. But I must
say that for the first time today, for the
first effort, I'm really pleased with
this. I also, I wanted to say that I was
really excited to see the large number of
study groups that had formed from around
the world and I wanted to also give a
special welcome to the people that are
clearly participating in the, in the class
from Iran and from Afghanistan. Two
countries which do not have the greatest
relationship officially with the United
States today but that is certainly not due
to any ill feeling on the part of
Americans and we certainly all believe
that these kinds of contact are the ones
that we should be having and I hope that
in our future online seminars that we can
have representatives from Iran and from
Afghanistan with us as well. So, I 'm
going to say goodbye to you all now. So,
thank all of you online for participating
in this wonderful experiment and I look
forward to seeing you this Monday with the
second lecture in the discussion boards
which I will be monitoring very careful
and of course, in our second online
seminar next Wednesday.