Let's continue our journey of these design
heuristics. Before we do, I'd like to
remind you that many of the interfaces
that we're gonna look at could fit into
multiple different multiple heuristics,
and the most important thing is to
identify the problem. If you identify and
fix the problem, the label is of secondary
importance. Our next heuristic is
recognition over recall. Create interfaces
that make objects, actions, options, and
directions visible or easily retrievable
And one of my favorite examples of this is
any time you see a post it note, that
probably means that the relevant
information isn't as ready at hand as it
ought to be. Here's a photograph I took of
one of our lunch meetings. And here you
can see we have shwarma and felafel. They
each have a number on them And we have a
code that's used to distinguish which
number means which kind of sandwich And of
course, the reason for this is that
someone spent all their time making these
delicious, and didn't take the time to
write out the whole label on it. So it's
understandable and fixable But, from an
interface design perspective, it would be
faster to find the chicken shawarma if it
was direc-, written directly on there, as
opposed to in code. [sound]. [sound]
Here's a screen shot of a ticket-buying
website, and what you can see is that it
gives you a couple of options like buy
tickets for today or for a future day.
There's a couple of problems from a
heuristics perspective with this screen
For starters, and we'll get to this in a
little bit, the layout is kind of all over
the place But also the thing that we're
going to look at here is the fact that we
have this intermediate screen which I
think could be done away with, with clever
design. It, for example, brings you to a
page that offers up show times for today
and offers you a dialogue box to switch
the day. By setting up reasonable defaults
you can avoid extra hurdles In addition to
leading with reasonable defaults; it can
be valuable to provide previews. This is a
screen shot of a web design too l where
there are many templates available.
However, all of the templates are shown in
textural listing, which is not well suited
for the task. You have to think through
whether that's what you want, and that's a
difficult thing to do reliably By contrast
this is a different web design tool that
offers previews of all of the templates
available, and it's much simpler to see if
that's the design that you'd like. Next
up, flexibility and efficiency And simple
and straight forward example of this is to
provide keyboard accelerator shortcuts and
similar things like that for experts. This
is the view menu of the Firefox web
browser And this is a great example of
offering flexibility and support for
experts in two ways. First, we can see
that there are keyboard shortcuts
available And second, the view source menu
will let you retrieve the page source of
any page you're looking at. So you can
look under the hood, not something that
most people want to do, valuable for
experts. This is the Expedia hotel search,
and it does a really nice job of making
the common cases quite easy to get to.
Popular cities are shown with a radio
button But also, if you'd like to go to a
less popular city, there's a free entry
field that you can type in anything that
you want. And so this is a nice example of
defaults with options. Flexible interfaces
can also foreground and push rather than
ambient information. This is a screen shot
of busy cow, which will allow you to view
the weather forecast on your weekly view
of your calendar. Here's another example
of productivity in the user interface.
This is Google's email. Which, if you
click spam on a recipient that it knows
how to unsubscribe you from, it will offer
the opportunity to directly unsubscribe
you from that email as well And I think
this is an example of how, if you're going
to be proactive in an interface, you need
to do it well And offer a clear,
immediate, task-relevant benefit. People
generally don't like proactive interfaces
that distract, break flow, or provide
irrelevant info rmation. Another nice
example of support for richer use is to
offer recommendations on a particular page
And so here you can see if you like this
one beverage here are other beverages you
might like [sound] and again, if you're
gonna offer recommendations, or other
kinds of pro activity, keep it relevant.
This is an example from Amazon of
discussion for a, for products that are
almost entirely unrelated to the product
that is being shown And it just distracts
from the user's main goal. Mostly they're
wondering why on Earth did these things
end up at the bottom of some completely
unrelated webpage And finally, flexibility
can be incredibly valuable. It is possible
to go overboard. This is a photograph from
Bill Moggridge who shows an interview with
a user who had hacked their remote control
to limit it to just the relevant
functionality that they needed. And so,
flexibility can sometimes be a tension
with minimalism. Our eighth heuristic is
aesthetic and minimalist design. When
people view your webpage for example,
they're viewing it on a screen, and so
they see not the entire page But one
screen's worth at a given time. What they
see is what's called above the fold. It
comes from newspapers. Here's an example
of a screen where the relevant
information, what the weather forecast is,
is not even visible anywhere above the
fold. Everything above the fold is all of
the chrome and extra stuff But the core
information you have to scroll down for
And to the extent that you're trying to
optimize for user experience, it would be
better to have the core information above
the fold. As we'll talk about in visual
design, if you're gonna use color and
other cues, have them mean something, and
do so judiciously. Here's an example of a
check out page that's using lots of
different colors, and has a real cacophony
in terms of its hierarchical organization
on screen, for no apparent purpose And
here's a screen shot from Goggle's help
system. Google is often thought of as an
example of minimalist design and they
often do this quit e well. I wanted to
show one example where, I think, some more
information could be stripped out, or
rather some more noise could be stripped
out And what I'm looking at in particular
is this stuff here, where all of the Table
boarders and other stuff are what you most
see, whereas, what you actually most care
about, is the data in the survey, and, so,
if you get rid of, all of the extra lines,
and chart junk, it could be clear to see,
the parts that you carried most about.
Here's a log in screen that I think does a
nice job in keeping the email address in
one place because it's right up to here
and then you get to say whether or not
you're a returning customer or a new
customer. If you're a returning customer
you enter your password or if you're a new
customer, like the screen shows here, you
create a new password and then type it in
and go on from there By contrast, this
flight search website has the exact same
information, number of stops, in two
separate places And it's possible that
this increased clarity. However, there is
a cost of complexity, and there's also a
cost of vertical screen real estate, where
by listing the same thing twice, you're
pushing other stuff down. Often by being
dynamic about what you show or figuring
out how to show things just once, you can
have all of the relevant information fit
more clearly and in a less cluttered way
on the screen. One of the easiest conceits
to make as a design team is that the
people using your site will care as deeply
and will want to spend as much time Using
the site as you've spent building the site
And so it can be easy to have feature
creep and lots of bells and whistles and
do dads But that's not necessarily what
people want. Here's an example of a
student loan website that offers you the
ability to add widgets to your home
screen. Now this is the kind of site that
you log into probably a couple times a
year? [laugh] It's not likely to be a site
that you're going to want to [inaudible]
with all sorts of gadgets. Next let's talk
about helping users recog nize diagnose
and recover from errors. One of the first
steps of doing this is making the problem
clearer, here's a hotel reservation site
where all it says is: mistake, month,
back. It's hard to know what to do. Here's
one that's a little bit better. It's a
registration site for an event. And what
we see here is that it says you must fill
out all the required fields. Okay, that's
a little better But which fields didn't I
fill out? This page is screens and screens
long. There's lots and lots of things that
need to be checked. Which of the myriad
things on this page did I forget to check?
Maybe you could show me just a page that
has the one or two things forgotten rather
than the whole pile of stuff and force me
to scroll through it again. Here's a
dialogue box that shows the error and
explains it clearly, but it doesn't offer
you much in terms of solving the problem.
It says that there's not enough space on
your iPod, too bad. A more effective
solution would be to offer some view into
what's taking up all the space, or to
offer reasonable ways of limiting the
amount of media that you're trying to put
on the device so that it can all fit And
in this particular case, more recent
versions of this application handle this
problem better. A common mistake in
writing error messages is to offer one
dialogue box for all of the possibilities.
Here's a screen shot of trying to open a
file where it doesn't know the file type.
And it says, the application that you
chose, null, could not found. Check the
file name, or choose another application.
Well this would be a whole lot better if
we were speaking the user's language. Null
may not be the best choice And also if we
offered up a reasonable application for
that file type. A lot of common tasks on
the web are search based tasks. So here's
a screenshot from searching for a flight.
Where the constraint specified yielded no
possible solution For complex search
tasks. If a user specifies an unreasonable
set of constraints, one of the most
powerful things that you can do as a des
igner is to offer a relaxation of those
constraints that makes this more workable.
Many years ago, I worked with Chuck Rich
at Mitsubishi Research in Boston And he
was working on a research system called
Collagen that would find ways to
intelligently relax these constraints.
Among other things, to help users get
their work done better. And this kind of
smart relaxation can be a really powerful
technique. I wanted to end talking about
errors on a good note. Here's a web
browser dialogue box that lets you know if
you go to a URL that it believes to be
suspect, it will let you know that you
probably don't wanna be here And it offers
to get you outta here and explain more
about why this webpage was blocked.
There's probably future further
innovations that could happen in this kind
of error work But I think that this is a
pretty good darn start and a lot better
than the way things used to be And that
brings us to our last heuristic, which is
better help and documentation. It can be
easy to think about help as somebody
else's problem and not part of the real
App. Fortunately, I think on the web, help
and documents have become more integrated.
One of my favorite examples for this is
learning programming systems where
websites like PHP, .NET can help you learn
programming systems by providing new
examples. Here is another example driven
strategy from UPS's website. It offers you
the opportunity to subscribe to a number
of mailing lists And if you wonder what
each of these mailing lists might give
you; on another screen I watched them
together here. It will show you examples
from each of those mailing lists of the
content you are likely to receive. That's
a really powerful kind of preview strategy
And here is an example of a print dialogue
box to tell you what the problem is, but
doesn't help you find the solution. For
starters, I think somebody wants to know,
is the stuff that's outside the margins
relevant? Is it just formally outside the
margins, but nothing's actually getting
cut off, or is there important document p
arts that I care about that are being cut
off from the page? And, what do you think
the most reasonable path is to solving
this problem? Should I change the page
size, or orientation, or move the header
and footer? Help me solve it. Here's a
dialogue box for the photo merge feature
of Adobe's Photoshop elements, which is a
very cool feature if you set it up right.
However you need to specify multiple
photos as input from the project bin And
this is something that the dialogue box
actually could do a better job of leading
you through. It could then say let me show
you and it could highlight the project bin
on the screen or something like that. Here
are two screenshots from eBay Unless we
have an interesting approach, where eBay
has built its own internal messaging
system. And if for the sake of argument we
decide that the right thing to do, and
that the internal messaging is better than
directly responding to email. I'm not sure
about that, but we'll go with it for now.
They've done a clever thing, which is,
when you reply, the reply mail address
says, hey, use the yellow button, and in
the middle of replying it you can see,
oops, I made a mistake. That's right I
need to use the internal messaging system.
It's an interesting hack And here's
another screenshot from e-bay on the right
hand side where when new functionality is
introduced for example the ability to
compare multiple options in your card it
can call that out inside the user
interface And I think the ability to
combine help directly into the user
interface is one of the most exciting
advances in this area And it's something
that was last common in previous desktop
applications And here's an example that I
think is interesting. This is the
un-subscription dialogue box for a mailing
list, and if you click, I receive too many
emails, it says wait, you can change the
frequency, and you have the opportunity to
receive mailing list mails at a less
frequent interval. I think that this is an
actually a really nice solution, because
sometimes you want to receive some mail,
but not too much. In other cases, maybe
you'll view this as harassing and you'll
wish that you could just be done with this
task quickly, but in either case, I
thought it was an interesting and creative
solution. [inaudible] If nobody needs to
know the terms of the licensing agreement
that's very reasonable But my hunch is
that the reason these things exist is
because they have consequence of some sort
the user should probably be informed about
And so if you're designing a site that has
terms for users think about is there a way
that you can at least summarize what the
key things somebody's agreeing to are
Without having them click through it or
having never even seen or read a lick of
the agreement at all And to close on a
positive note, one nice thing that you can
do with help on a website is to help
people have fun Filling out forms can
often be really boring, and here's an
example from a hotel website where one of
the options has a little joke on the
inside and so that, and so that bit of
levity can help increase the user
experience.