There are several different ways that
interfaces can help people think more
fluently by distributing the cognition
into artifacts in the world. When
interfaces help people distributed
cognition, it can encourage
experimentation, it can scaffold learning
and reduce errors through redundancy. It
can show only the differences that matter,
it can convert small calculation into fast
perception, it can support chunking
specially by experts, it can increase
efficiency of interactions and it can
facilitate collaboration. Let's go through
this one at a time. Here's now a video
game that, that many of you all know. This
is the Tetris video game And there was a
very clever study that David Koresh and
Paul Maglio at UC San Diego ran where they
looked at Tetris players playing Tetris
and what they found was really
interesting. In textures as you may know
you can use keys to move objects
surrounding the screen and at a certain
point you can hit the space bar that drop
the object and try and get a row of field
blocks. Moving and rotating pieces on the
screen may seem like a waste of time
because you have a limited amount of time
before the block hits the bottom so how do
you use that most efficiently? It turns
out that people move the block around the
screen more than they in some purely
theoretical sense need to so in essence,
I'm trying out different places that the
blocks could go. Maybe this is just for
novices that when you're learning Tetris
you need to feel things out but as you
become more of an expert that's no longer
the case, exactly the opposite.
[inaudible] found that experts actually
rely more heavily on moving objects on the
world. And what they were doing is they
were distributing the cognitive effort of
what if scenarios. What if I place it over
here or what if I place it over there? You
absolutely can do that in your mind But it
turns that in this case, for most people
it's cheaper to do it out in the world to
be able to turn the cognitive task of
reasoning about all of the what if
scenarios into a perceptual task of, oh
yeah, that block would work perfectly
right there. It saves you the effort of
having two in particular mentally rotate
to different pieces to figure out how they
would fit into the screen. Here's another
example from the learning sciences. There
are called Montesorri Blocks. And what we
have here are beads that provide a
physical representation or number
specially for young children. Numbers are
really abstract concepts difficult to, to
get your head around and these physical
[inaudible] can help the addition,
multiplication and other simple arithmetic
operation. So, for example if I'm gonna
take three And multiplied y three to get
three squared. Well I can see that I have
three by three, I have a square and I can
see that it's compost of nine bids and
there other multiplication options that
you could with these also and by having
this redundant information by taking an
abstract concept and redefining it and
making it concrete it can help scaffold
learning and reduce errors. The Montessori
Blocks example and the Tetris example show
us the power of providing a visual or
physical instantiation of abstract ideas.
So what makes a good representation of
this sort? Well, it, you should show the
information that you need and nothing
else. And, what these representation
should do is it should enable to kinds of
tasks that users wanna do like comparison
and exploration and problem solving. And
if that's seem to abstract or maybe
obvious, let's take a look at this example
from the London Underground. This subway
map was introduced about a century ago and
it was one of the very first maps to
introduce a brand new idea in map design
of abstracting the layout of the tracks
from the underlying physical geography.
This London subway map, The map would show
what the geography was and so long things
were long and short things were short and
if it the tracks wandered because that's
the way that it works and the tracks on
the map would wander because that's the
way things worked. And with the
underground map designers realized was
that. The most common task for subway
writers is to figure out how to get from
point A to point B and all of these
additional details of faithfulness to the
underlying topology was getting in the way
of that A to B task more than it was
helping it. And so what they did is they
stripped that a lot of that unnecessary
detail turning this into vertical,
diagonal, and horizontal lines. So there
are some representation between the layout
on the map and the lay out on the real
world. North is north, and South is south,
and things roughly head in the direction
that they do in the real world but the
detail is stripped out and this makes it
much easier to be able to figure out how
to get between connections. Another thing
that they did is they introduced a century
later we would call a focus plus context
representation for the map. In the center
of London, the subway stations are very
densely packed so that area is expanded
out. It consumes more of the map real
estate. As you get out toward the suburbs,
the stations are fewer and further
between. As oppose to that taking up 90
percent of the map because it's 90 percent
of the space. Those stations are actually
scorned because if you know you need to go
Northeast to a particular station then the
exact distance is involved are most of the
time less relevant. Now of course with
constitutes of good representation is a
course task specific and so what you can
see is that by making some task easier
like getting from A to B when you know A
and B or being able to navigate the center
of London more effectively. You've
compromised other tasks and so for
somebody who may need to make decisions
about what's tough to get off at based on
some underlying Topography or another task
that's compromised is by virtue of the
distance between the stations on the map
not lining up between the distances
between the stations in the world. You can
make poor judgments about what's close and
what's far in the center you may believe
things are far, far apart when they are
really close and on the suburbs, you may
believe from the map that things are
closer than they actually are And so
nearly all representation design is about
fitness to task. Here's a temperature map
from the weather underground. It shows the
temperature at each location at bay area,
geo-referenced so that the temperature
number is placed right on top of that
physical location. What do you think the
benefits and drawbacks of this
representation? What's it good for and
what's it a problem for. If you know the
physical coordinate that you'd like, the
temperature for say for example what
temperature is it along the coast and I
don't care or don't know the exact name of
the town. This works incredibly well. It's
also a reasonable interface in some sense
for trying to get a [inaudible] of what
are the temperatures like in the area over
all I could see for example. As I head
inland the temperature tends to get
warmer. There are a lot of ways in which
we could make this better so right now
every temperature is shown identically no
matter what temperature it is which means
it's hard to scan. I have to read every
single temperature one by one. I could
make this better if instead I had the
temperature number somehow the color or
size of the temperature, number correspond
to the weather, But if we're going to
start mapping the variables of the map to
something like color, we need to be
careful to get it right. This is an
example that comes from Edward Tufte. His
books on Visual Design and the Graphical
representations of data are fantastic and
I strongly encourage you to read them. In
this map, we see how a computer scientist
might make a mapping for Japan. This is
showing the height above or below sea
level as color and what you can see is the
depth below sea level is represented by
the color spectrum Roy G. By now, one of
the challenges of hue is that it's not an
additive representation. So, so it's not
really a strong ordering that we give to
the colors perceptually. Its substitute of
representation that red and yellow are
qualitativ ely different but we don't
automatically have a more than or less
than relationship between the two, Another
problem on this representation is, it's
very difficult by gland to tell what's
higher and what's lower in the sea.
Conversely the individual isosurfaces, the
individual Chunks of this particular depth
really pop out like to me for example, the
yellow depth pops out very strongly and
that shape really comes to the attention
for which if you are making a rock and
roll poster for the Fillmore would be
awesome but if you're trying to get a
sense of the contour of the sea, what
become salient to you, the outlines for
what's 400 meters below sea level. It
probably just not that relevant so how
could we continue our theme of using color
as representational queue but how that be
more meaningful than you might see in this
case where we're mapping it to the color
spectrum. And here's Edward Tufte's
redesign which I think is much better.
There's a couple of things that I really
like about the representation here. The
first one is the all of the things that
are above sea level are brown, are kind of
an earth tone. So, we're leveraging our
intuitions about physical world and using
that metaphorically for the map. So, the
land colored stuff is and similarly all of
the water is blue, the water-colored stuff
is water. And further more we can see how
the intensity or the luminance of that
color blue changes with depth and the
deeper blues are darker blues. Which
corresponds to our physical intuitions and
of course, water doesn't really get that
much darker at that kind of depth that
we're talking about here. Our intuition
about darker colors being deeper comes
from much shallower depths but the idea,
you can leverage this thing that we all
know that water right by the shore is, is
a paler color and as you get more of it,
it, it gets darker. So, this is a really
wonderful way to see that these darker
areas here are deeper than the shallow
areas here. With the lower underground
map, we saw how the representation of the
map, what makes a good representation was
intrinsically tied up with the task that
the user is doing. Similarly, what makes a
good representation is also dependent on
what a user's expertise is. And a
wonderful example of this comes from Herb
Simon and David Chase in the early 1970s.
They were looking at chess as an exemplar
domain for trying to understand expertise.
One of the things that they observed was
that expert chess players were much better
at being able to remember the
configuration of a chess board. You can
imagine a couple hypotheses for this. So,
one of them would be experts were born
with a better memory for that kind of
thing or similarly, experts by virtue of
their ten thousand hours of training have
trained themselves up to build up that
muscle and be very good at remembering
that kind of thing. Now this turns out to
be the case. Experts are much better at
remembering a configuration of the board.
[sound] But only if it's an actual game so
if the configuration of the chest board is
the configuration of the chest board could
be exports to a fantastic job of
remembering But if you arranged the pieces
on the board in a way that chest plate
could not ever achieve, the experts
actually do know better than analysis at
all. And so what we're seeing is that the
ability of experts to chunk things and
have higher memory capacity is because
they are able to leverage their knowledge
about the domain. Game design or user
interface design are both concerned with
how easy or hard is it for a user to
accomplish a particular task. The
difference is often designers wanna make
it hard, the right hard and the interface
game designers wanna make it that things
easy And so we can learn from this chest
example and we can ask the question to
interface designers, can we make
interfaces more chunkable? Can we make
interactions that can be accomplished in
one chunk? And therefore replace a lower
load on our memory and make it easier for
users to work with. A great example of
this comes from Bill Buxton who looked at
being abl e to move text between locations
on a document. And in a common desktop
user interface today one common operation
will either keyboard short cuter and menu
command to cut some texts and then you
move the cursor to a new location and you
paste that text. That's three different
operations and in between, if you got
interrupted, you might forget what's in
the copy [inaudible]. In fact, I'm sure
that happened to all of us at some point.
What Bobston realized is what if you could
turn all of these to a gesture user
interface in the one command. So, maybe I
could grab a text that I want. Draw a new
location and drop it right there. That's
being much better There's never a time
where I could be interrupted and loose
state because all of the state is
maintained in this continuous gesture.
We've all heard the saying that pictures
worth ten thousand words. As interface
designers, we're tasked with the project
of representing the information to the
user and one task that we commonly have to
deal with is, should we represent
information usually? Or should we
represent information textually. The
answer of course is it depends but one
time when representing information
visually can be much more effective is
when you can convert slow reasoning tasks
into fast perception tasks by virtue of
making them visually salient. We saw that
with the map example. In that case, both
the colorings of the map were visual. But
one, it was much easier to just add a
glance understand what's going on in good
coloring. And the fore coloring, you have
the reason about it much more slowly and
the wrong things kept popping out. If you
think about a table of numbers, it can
often be difficult to see trends whereas
if you represent that same information
visually, it can often pop out what the
high points, the low points, trends,
outlines, all of that becomes salient and
automatically visible to you.