In this video, we're going to talk about
assigning participants to conditions And
one of the most basic questions you can
ask about this is, should every
participant use every alternative. To
illustrate this, we're going to walk
through an example. We're going to see the
trade off that are intrinsic to different
approaches that you can take here. In this
study we're going to compare smart vacuum
cleaner With more traditional vacuum
cleaner. As you remember from last time,
one of the first questions we should ask
about this are, what are the measures do
we want something that is faster, or
cleaner, or less fatigue that are
ergonomics, lower environmental impact,
affordability, easy views, fewer errors.
Any of these are valid measures you might
keep track of them all. For our example
here though, we're, we're going to pick
two. We're going to go with the faster and
we're going to go with cleaner. So our
manipulation is going to be back in type
and our measure is going to be speed and
cleanliness. To help illustrate this
example, I'm going to recruit the help of
my graduate students and TA's. And so here
they are. One thing you can imagine is
that you assign half of them to each
condition. That's called the between
subjects design and so we could assign
half of them to the robot interface And we
can assign half of them to the traditional
interface. So, Chinma, Nicholas and Alex
get the robot And Dan, Ronjita and Jesse
get the traditional one. And let's say for
example, that the robotic interface
performs better, faster and cleaner. With
only six people, it's hard to say whether
it's because the, the vacuum cleaner there
is better or whether the three people that
we have been assigned to it Chinma,
Nicholas and Alex were better cleaners
than Dan, Jesse and Ronjita. So, the
strategy is within subject design where we
could have everybody use both interfaces.
Wonder what they're going to use first, if
they use the old interface face or gotten
practice and maybe extra good or maybe
tired when they get to use the new one And
vice versa. So between subje ct's designs,
have to worry about individual differences
within subject's designs have a worry
about ordering effects. Is there some way
that we can get the best of both worlds?
Well, how might we address these ordering
effects? Well, one thing that we could do
is we could take half of the people and
have them try one interface first. In the
other path and try the, try the other
interface first. Counter balancing has a
couple of nice properties. For starters,
you can treat it as completely a between
subject's design if you look at only the
first task that people do. And hopefully,
the benefit that you get from practicing
or the discriminative fatigue is roughly
the same in both condition and both even
itself about and so kind of balancing
watches out some of those concerns. There
are times where this is isn't the case and
that's a great time to use between
subjects design. To minimize the learning
effects is probably best to make the first
and second task different. So in this
case, we might have people clean the D
School as their first task and clean the
Gates building as their second. This also
has the added benefit of giving us some
more ecological validity by trying out a
couple of different environment so we know
it's not just the Gates building that's
better cleaned by robots. It also has the
benefit to build the D School and the
Gates building are clean. How about
individual differences? Should we try to
balance for shirt color, hair length,
gender, or whether the picture in the icon
is square-ish or more rectangular? It
depends on whether you think it's going to
make a difference in the study or whether
one might possibly believe that it would
make a difference in the study. Simple
thing to do is choose the random
assignment. We'll talk about more
sophisticated techniques in a couple of
slides. Okay. So now we know a couple of
ways of dealing with two different
alternatives. But what if we have three?
With three alternatives you can use
something called the Latin Square. I'll
explain how this works with thr ee
conditions that generalizes more. In a
classic Latin square design, each person
is going to use all three conditions.
You'll randomly divide your participants
up in three different groups. The first
group is going to get the first one first,
the second one second and the third one
third. The second group two, three, one
And the third one three, one, two, So
again, everybody gets all there conditions
But their order changes and if you look at
any particular order segment so like what
people see first or what people see
second, what people see third. You can see
that is also evenly balanced across the
three conditions. Maybe choose between
subject approaches or within subject's
approach. The most important thing to do
is to make sure that the odds that any
particular participant ends up in a
particular condition or particular
condition ordering is completely random as
even. We can illustrate this as with an
example. Say you wanted to find out
whether people were faster typing in the
morning or typing in the afternoon and you
allow to people to come in whenever they
want. What if you will ever have
preference for the morning, morning people
or faster typers and people who have a
preference for the afternoon? Your
conclusion is that morning, maybe the
morning was faster but that's not right
because it's just the morning people who
are faster not that there's something
about the, the morning or maybe not, you
can't say confound. It's possible that the
causal reason was population difference
and not experimental manipulation This
confounds, as well rather than economic is
so hard and computing correlations but
there is no manipulations. Random
assignment as tool number one in achieving
a effective manipulation. So in our typing
case you would want to assign people to be
in either the morning condition or the
afternoon condition. The morning and
afternoon example can seem kind of
stylized but it shows a lot of real world.
For example, if you're running a website,
one easy thing that you might do is show
everybody one alternativ e on one day and
one alternative on the next. Well there
may be a difference between those days.
We'll talk more about running experiments
later on but for now I wanted to point out
that the key is, if you're going to do
something like this make sure that people
are randomly assigned. Easiest way in most
cases is, is between subjects design where
you assign people as they come in to see
either one interface or the other. Here's
another example of the importance of
random assignment. In the 1930s, some
studies were run at the Western Electric
factory outside Chicago called Hawthorne
and the plan was pretty simple. Find out
whether changes in lightning levels
affected productivity. So, experiments
came in. Raise the lightning levels,
productivity goes up. Then they tried
lowering the light levels, productivity
went up Tried a whole bunch of
combinations. After each intervention,
productivity went up. The conclusion of
course is that it's the active intervening
rather than the light levels itself which
was the major course behind the
productivity change presumably other the
workers felt like people cared about them
or the excitement of the experiment or
whatever. That was the driving factor. In
recent years some economist, have
questioned whether in fact there was a
Hawthorne effect at the Hawthorne plan. If
you're curious you can Google more about
that. In either case the name is stuck and
it means a case where what you're seeing
is your effect is the result of the
intervention rather than the thing that
you're trying to study and you can avoid
this with random assignment. We talked
about counter balancing the order of
conditions that participants experience.
You can also counter balance how you
assign people the conditions. Say for
example you're worried that typing speed
will differentially affect something in
your interface; you're building a new
spread sheet or something like that. You
could use a pretest to establish typing
speed ahead of time and use that to assign
people to conditions. There's many
techniques for doing this. Simplest way to
do it is just look at high speed typers
versus low speed typers. The key no matter
what is that each participant has an equal
chance of ending up in either condition.
Let's walk through an example. If you can
pretest everyone ahead of time, most
likely that you can do is form match
pairs. So say we get the typing speed that
we see here, after ordering they look like
this. We can group them into pairs and
then for each pair, we can conceptually
flip a coin about which of them is going
to land in which of the two conditions. I
got one of these dollar coins to the take
out machine the other day and it'll do
well for flipping, So for 35 and 37 Heads
so we'll put 35 down here. First
condition, 37 goes in the second And for
57 versus 59. It's tails so 59 goes here.
[sound]. There is the heads so that gives
us 61, 68 Entails And, that gives us 99
goes here and 70 goes here. By doing this
match pairs, you're balancing out the
performance of people approximately in
each condition. And, by having some random
list in there, you're ensuring that you
don't get some accidental statistical
artifacts that creep in by saying sign all
your odds here and all your evens there.
The type of people are coming in online so
you can't pretest people for the
experiment. But what you can do is you can
pick some threshold that you think is in
about the middle. So, if for typing, you
might say 65 words a minute and as people
come in. You can check whether they're
above or below that threshold and label
are high, high or low, fast or slow typers
based on that. So 35 we would say is low.
40 is low. 90 is high. 68 is high and so
on and you can assign them to your two
different conditions. We call them A, B
High and low, So our first low person to
come in 35, Tails, so that will go to B
And then the balance that out 40 will go
heads. Next time we got a pair of lows,
we're going to flip the coin again and
we're going to do that for the highs also.
So the highs come in and, heads. So our
first high will go to A and our secon d
high will go to B. You don't need to make
sure that you had even numbers of high and
low typers unless you worry about that
making the material difference on in the
outcome. In fact, you have many
participants; you can look at this, two by
two grid and compare the outcomes of the
four cells. What you do need to make sure
is that there are the same number of fast
typers of high in a and in b and the same
number or slow typers are low in a and in
b. There's a lot of ways that you can do
these kinds of counter-balancing. In
general, all of them much are giving the
same thing which is trying to help
[inaudible] enlarge numbers that you get
in a between subject study work a little
bit faster. Now, there's a danger of
assigning people based on a pretest that I
like to warn you about. Say, we want to
pretest for coins that are more like to
come up ahead. So, I have some coins here.
I can flip each of these a couple of times
and. Okay. That one's heads more. So it
was really heads more. Tails. Tails. That
was tails. Heads And what else, [sound]
So, we have three coins that had a heavy
tendency and three coins that have a
tailey tendency. Now, we can feed them a
the snack so we can a bagel. In fact, this
is the same bagel in the last lecture. So
with bagels, so it's not such a fresh
bagel anymore. But nonetheless it will
give our coins some sustenance so we can
give them each, each sound of bagel and we
want to see whether our [sound] Heady
coins become more or so and whether tailey
coins become more or so. So, we think by
the natural tendencies of this coins is
one direction by feeding them. I, I think
that may make them more or so. So, the
questions we're going to ask is whether
the snacking increases the natural
tendencies of coins. And we can re-flip
all of these and I wouldn't inflict that
on you right now. But you can try yourself
and what you'll see, of course, is that
none of these coins really had a, a
tendency towards head or tail, it's just
that on a small number of samples. You
know if you came out with a little b it
more heads, if you came out a little bit
of more tails and if you flip them again
there will be no co-relation between their
heads in tendency in the first half and
their heads in tendency in the second
half. To make it a little more exciting
than just the six coins that I have in my
pocket, I decided to generate 30 coins in
excel and I flip them each 21 times and
you can see the results here of how many
heads each got out of 21 toss. I picked an
odd number so that it would have to be
either heady or taily on the hole. And
what we can see if we rank them by number
is it turns out actually fifteen of them
had a head tendency. Fifteen had a tail
and the average of the heads is 12.9 and
the average of our tail tendency is 8.3.
Now, after I flip in the snack, I can flip
that again. And I have highlighted in
yellow and bold it again that the, the
numbers that have a, a head tendency and
there's essentially no correlation between
here. It does turn out that our heads our
initial heads. Have an average of 10.7
after eating the bagel and our initial
tails have an average of 9.6. So we can
see that both of these regressed towards
the mean, both of these are closer towards
the expected value of ten and a half. We
may see a perceived different here between
the 9.6 and the 10.7. In the future
lecture we'll learn how to test whether
that's a real difference or whether that's
a statistical mirage. So this danger is
actually is very real and it shows up all
the time in statistical analysis of things
like low performing schools increasing the
next year or high performing schools
decreasing. The assignment problem that
results in regression to the mean is when
you're making something like a dividing
line and you're using the assignment so
everybody who scores high goes up,
everybody who scores low goes down and
then you measure their performance
subsequently. If in steady you use a
pretest to counter balance like we did
with the typist, so we put high and low
speed typists in both conditions, then you
no longer have that worr y about
regression to the mean. So, the major
question that we tackled here is should
every participant use every alternative?
And whether emerged was three nature
strategies. And in within subject design,
everybody tries all the options. This has
big benefits in terms of recruiting
participants. You get more, more work out
of its coercion and it works really well
if you are not working about learning or
practice or exposures and trying one
version to pollute the other one And in
between subject study, each person tries
one condition. This requires more people
and you may want to consider
counterbalancing for fair assignment. It
has the benefit of course that each
participant is uncorrupted and for this
reason is the most common techniques that
we see in things like web studies And if
you use it between subject's design, you
can use counter balancing to help even
things out. What I offered today is just a
really high level over view and I'm
necessarily glossed over a whole bunch of
important details but I wanted to give you
an initial lay or land for running
studies. If you're interested in more,
more reading in this area. My favorite
book in this area is David Martin's book
Doing Psychology Experiments. I'll see you
next time.