In this lecture, we're gonna talk about
trying out your interface with people, and
doing so in a way that you can improve
your designs based on what you learned.
One of the most common things that people
ask when running studies is, do you like
my interface? And it's a really natural
thing to ask because on some level it's
what we all want to know. But this is
really problematic on a whole lot of
levels. For one it's not very specific and
so sometimes people will try and make this
better and so they'll, they'll improve it
by doing something like how much do you
like my interface on a one to five scale?
Or this is a useful interface. Agree or
disagree on a one to five scale? And this
adds some kind of patina of scientificness
to it but really its just the same thing
you're asking somebody. Do you like my
interface? And people are nice so they're
going to say, sure I like your interface.
This is the please the experimenter bias.
And this can be especially strong when
there are social or cultural or power
differences between the experimenter and
the people that you are trying out your
interface with. For example [inaudible]
and colleagues showed these in effect in
India, where this effect was exacerbated
when the examiner was white. Now you
should not take this to mean that you
shouldn't have your developers try out
stuff with users. Being the person who is
both the developer and the person who is
trying stuff out is incredibly valuable.
And one example I like a lot of this is by
Mike Krieger, one of the Instagram
founders is also a former master student
and TA of mine. And Mike, when he left
Stanford and joined Silicon Valley, every
Friday afternoon he would bring people
into the lab into his office and have them
try out whatever they were working on that
week. And so that way they were able to
get this regular feedback each week and
the people who were building those systems
got to see real people trying them out.
This can be nails on a chalkboard painful
but you'll also learn a ton. So how do we
get beyond do you like my interface? The
basic strategy that we're going to talk
about today is being able to use specific
measures and concrete questions to be able
to deliver meaningful results. One of the
problems of do you like my interface is
compared to what? And I think one of the
reasons people say, yeah sure is that
there's no comparison point and so one
thing that's really important is when
you're measuring the effectiveness of your
interface, even informally, it's really
nice to have some kind of comparison. It's
also important think about well, what's
the yard stick? What constitutes good in
this arena? What are the measures that
you're gonna use? So how can we get beyond
do you like my interface? One of the ways
that we can start out is by asking a base
rate question like, what fraction of
people click on the first link in a search
results page? Or what fraction of students
come to class? Once we start to measure
correlations things get even more
interesting like, is there a relationship
between the time of day a class is
offered? And how many students attend it?
Or is there a relationship between the
order of a search result and the
click-through rate? For both students and
click-through, there can be multiple
explanations. For example, if there are
fewer students that attend early morning
classes, is that a function of when
students want to show up? Or is that a
good function of when good professors want
to teach? With the click-through example,
there are also two kinds of explanations.
If lower placed links yield fewer clicks.
Is that because the links are of
intrinsically poor quality or is it
because people just click on the first
link? They don't, they don't bother
getting to the second one even if it might
be better. To isolate the effect of
placement and identifying it as playing a
casual role, you'd need to isolate that as
a variable by say, randomizing the order
or search results. As we start to talk
about these experiments, let's introduce a
few terms that are gonna help us. The
multiple different conditio ns that we
try, that's the thing we are manipulating.
For example, the time of the class or the
location of a particular link on a search
result page. These manipulations are
independent variables because they are
independent of what the user does. They
are in the control of the experimenter.
Then we are going to measure what the user
does and those measures are called
dependent variables because they depend on
what the user does. Common measures in HCI
include things like task completion time.
How long does it take somebody to complete
a task? For example, find something I want
to buy, create a new account, order an
item. Accuracy. How many mistakes did
people make? And were those fatal errors
or were those things that they were able
to quickly recover from? Recall. How much
does a person remember afterward, or after
periods of non-use? And emotional
response. How does the person feel about
the tasks being completed? Were they
confident, were they stressed? Would the
user recommend this system to a friend?
So, your independent variables are this
things that you manipulate, your dependent
variables are this things that you
measure. How reliable is your experiment?
If you ran this again, would you see the
same results? That's the internal validity
of an experiment. So, have a precise
experiment, you need to better remove the
confounding factors. Also, it's important
to study enough people so that the result
is unlikely to have been by chance. You
may be able to run the same study over and
over and get the same results but it may
not matter in some real world sense and
the external validity is the
generalizability of your results. Does
this apply only to eighteen year olds in a
college classroom? Or does this apply to
everybody in the world? Let's bring this
back to HCI and talk about one of the
problems you're likely to face as, as a
designer. I think one of the things that
we commonly want to be able to do is to be
able to ask something like, is my cool new
approach better than the industry
standard? Because aft er all, that's why
you're making the new thing. Now, one of
the challenges with this, especially early
on in the design process is that you may
have something which is very much in its
prototype stages and something that is the
industry standard is likely to benefit
from years and years of refinement. And at
the same time, it may be stuck with years
and years of cruft which may or may not be
intrinsic to its approach. So if you
compare your cool new tool to some
industry standard, there is two things
varying here. One is the fidelity of the
implementation and the other one of course
is the approach. Consequently, when you
get the results, you can't know whether to
attribute the results to fidelity or
approach or some combination of the two.
So we're going to talk about ways of
teasing apart those different causal
factors. Now, one thing I should say right
off the bat is there are some times where
it may be more or less relevant whether
you have a good handle on what the causal
factors are. So for example, if you're
trying to decide between two different
digital cameras, at the end of the day,
maybe all you care about is image quality
or usability or some other factor and
exactly what the, makes that image quality
better or worse or any other element along
the way may be less relevant to you. If
you don't have control over the variables
then identifying cause may not always be
what you want. But when you are a
designer, you do have control over the
variables and that's when it is really
important to as you retain cause. Here's
an example of a study that came out right
when the iPhone was released, done by a
research firm User Centric, and I'm going
to read from this news article here.
Research firm User Centric has released a
study that tries to gauge how effective
the iPhone's unusual on screen keyboard
is. The goal is certainly a noble one but
I cannot say the survey's approach results
in data that makes much sense. User
Centric brought in twenty owners of other
phones. Half had qwerty keyboards, half
had ordin ary numeric phones, with
keypads. None were familiar with the
iPhone. The research involved having the
test subjects enter six sample test
messages with the phones that they already
had, and six with the iPhone. The end
result was that the iPhone newbies took
twice as long to enter text with an iPhone
as they did with their own phones and made
lots more typos. So let's critique this
study and talk about it's benefits and
drawbacks. Here's the webpage directly
from User Centric. What's our manipulation
in this study? Well the manipulation is
going to be the input style. How about the
measure in the study? It's going to be the
words per minute. And there's absolutely
value in being able to measure the initial
usability of the iPhone. For several
reasons, one is if you're introducing new
technology it's beneficial if people are
able to get up to speed pretty quickly.
However it's important to realize that
this comparison is intrinsically unfair
because the users of the, the previous
cell phones were experts at that input
modality and the people who are using the
iphone are novices in that modality. And
so it seems quite likely that the iPhone
users, once they become actual users are
gonna get better over time and so if
you're not used to something the first
time you try it, that may not be a deal
killer, and it's certainly not an apples
to apples comparison. Another thing that
we don't get out of this article is, is
this difference significant? So we read
that each person who typed six messages in
each of two conditions and so they did
their own device in the iPhone or vice
versa. Six messages each and that the
iPhone users were half the speed of the,
or rather the people typing with the
iPhone were half as fast as when they got
to type with a mini qwerty and the device
that they were accustomed to. So while
this may tell us something about the
initial usability of the iPhone in terms
of the long usability, long-term
usability, you know I don't think we get
so much out of this here. If you weren't s
atisfied by that initial data, you're in
good company, neither were the authors of
that study. So they went back a month
later and they ran another study where
they brought in 40 new people to the lab
who were either iPhone users or Qwerty
users or nine key users. And now it's more
of an apples to apples comparison in that
they are going to test people that are
relatively experts in these different
modalities. After about a month on the
iPhone you're probably starting to ask in
terms of your performance. Definitely it
gets better over time, even past a month
but you know a month starts to get more
reasonable. And what they found was that
iPhone users and Qwerty users were about
the same. And in terms of speed and that
the numeric keypad users were much slower.
So once again our manipulation is going to
be input style and we're going to measure
speed. This time we're also going to
measure error rate. And what we see is
that iPhone users and Qwerty users are
essentially the same speed. However, the
iPhone users make many more errors. Now,
one thing I should point out about the
study is that each of the different
devices was used by a different group of
people. And it was done this way so that
each, each device was used by somebody who
is comfortable and had experience with
working with that device. And so, we
removed the worry that you had newbies
working on these devices. However,
especially in 2007, there may have been
significant differences in who the people
were who were using the early adopters of
the 2007 iPhone or maybe business users
were particularly drawn to the Qwerty
devices or people who had better things to
do with their time than send e-mail on
their telephone or using the nine key
devices. And so, while this comparison is
better than the previous one, the
potential for variation between the user
populations is still problematic. If what
you'd like to be able to claim is
something about the intrinsic properties
of the device and may at least in part
have to do with the users. So, what are
some st rategies for fairer comparison? To
brainstorm a couple of options one thing
you could do is insert your approach in to
your production setting and this may seem
like a lot of work, sometimes it is but in
the age of the web this is a lot easier
than it used to be. And it's possible even
if you don't have access to these server
of the service that you're comparing
against. You can use things like a proxy
server or client type scripting to be able
to put your own technique in and have an
apples to apples comparison. A second
strategy for neutralizing the environment
difference between a production version
and your new approach is to make a version
of the production thing in the same style
as your new approach. That also makes them
equivalent in terms of their
implementation fidelity. A third strategy
and one that's used commonly in research,
is to scale things down so you're looking
at just a piece of the system at a
particular point in time. That way you
don't have to worry about implementing a
whole big, giant thing. You can just focus
on one small piece and have that
comparison be fair. And the fourth
strategy is that when expertise is
relevant, train people up. Give them the
practice that they need so that they can
start at least hitting that asymptote in
terms of performance and you can get a
better read than, what they would be as
newbies. So now to close out this lecture
if somebody asks you the question, is
interface x better than interface y? You
know that we're off to a good start
because we have a comparison. However, you
also know to be worried. What does better
mean? And often, in a complex system,
you're going to have several measures.
That's totally cool. There's a lot of
value in being explicit though about what
it is you mean by better. What are you
trying to accomplish? What are you trying
to approve? And if anybody ever tells you
that their interface is always better,
don't believe them because nearly all of
the time the answer is going to be, it
depends. And the interesting question is,
what does it depend on? Most interfaces
are good for something and not for others.
For example if you have a tablet computer
where all of the screen is devoted to
display, that is going to be great for
reading, for web browsing, for that kind
of activity, looking at pictures. Not so
good if you want to type a novel. So here,
we've introduced controlled comparison as
a way of finding the smoking gun, as a way
of inferring cause. And often for, when
you have only two conditions, we're gonna
talk about that as being a minimal pairs
design. As a practicing designer, the
reason to care about what's causal is that
it gives you the material to make a better
decision going forward. A lot of studies
violate this constraint. And, that gets
dangerous because it doesn't, it prevents
you from being able to make sound
decisions. I hope that the tools that
we've talked about today and in the next
several lectures will help you become a
wise skeptic like our friend in this XKCD
Comic. I'll see you next time.