[sound] People are remarkable and all
sorts of ways, But an attention in short
term memory are limited resources.
Fortunately, there's hope. The
representation provided by language,
gesture, drawings, and objects helps us
communicate and reason And importantly for
design, different representations can
facilitate or hinder different thoughts.
The inside of today's lecture is the ways
in which we and the world well organized
and represent ideas can have a drastic
impact on our cognitive abilities for
better and for worse. Things can help us
think and you can leverage this as a
designer. Let's start with an example that
comes from Don Norman and [inaudible].
It's a really strange diner and in this
diner the wait staff is not so good And
three, the three people at the, at the
diner ordered oranges but they ended up on
the wrong plates and your job, you can try
this at home, is to help sort out which
orange belongs on which plate. And so, the
way that the, the orange puzzle works is
you need to order the oranges by size,
largest to smallest, left to right. Only
one orange can be transferred at a time,
and orange can only be transferred to a
plate on which it'll be in the largest And
only the largest orange on the plate can
be transferred to another plate and so on.
I have I have three oranges here. Our
recording got a little bit delayed because
somebody ate this little orange so I had
to go back to the market and get another
one But, but we have an orange now and let
me show you how this work. So, I'm gonna
lay this out At my diner coffee. >> Here
you have the three oranges that, as
delivered by the wave staff and you can
see there in the wrong were the, the
largest ones in the middle and the middle
ones over here and the smallest one which
needs to be over here so over on this
side. And so to help save these diners one
of the TA's that you've seen in online
class, Alex is gonna come and, and sort
this out. >> Oh man, this is very
difficult. So I have to only transfer one
orange at a time, right? >> One orange at
a t ime. >> And it can only be to the
biggest plate. >> It, it has to be the
largest orange on the plate. >> Okay. So,
can I transfer this here? >> No, cuz then
it won't be the largest orange. >> Okay.
So, can I transfer it here? >> You got it.
>> Great And then kinda transfer this one
over here? >> Sure. >> And then this one
here. >> You got it. Well done. >> Thank
you And there's a couple other diners who
got similar orders, they all wanted bagels
and so. So, that the first course of
oranges, the second course is gonna be
bagels. The real bagel's puzzle is why you
can't get a decent bagel in California.
But the bagel puzzle that we have for
today is, is a little bit different. So,
we have our largest bagel, medium bagel,
smallest bagel. So, the plan is the same
except with the bagels, you have the
ability to stack them. You can out a
larger bagel on top of the smaller bagel
but not a smaller bagel on top of the
larger one. And so, at any point in time,
just like the oranges, it needs to be the
largest one on the plate and this is in
reverse order and Alex is gonna help us
again rearranging the bagels so that the
largest is on the left and the smallest is
on the right. >> Cool. So it has to be the
largest, right? >> Large is on the left.
>> So I can move this one here. >> You got
it. >> I can move this one here. >> Yup.
>> And I can move this one here. >> Yup.
There you go, well done. >> Now all of the
diners are happy assuming of course, its
New York bagels which they are not but
that's close enough for now. So, that's
our, that's our bagels came for today. You
can try these ate home and what you see is
that the fact that the bagels represent
some of the constraints of the problem. In
the physical structure, makes it much
easier to remember the state. You don't
have to remember which of these two bagels
is larger and therefore movable because
the larger on is on top, you're not gonna
move this medium sized bagel underneath
and that makes it all a lot easier when a,
when a representation of the problem in
forces th at constraints in the rule of
the problem And you can think of this a
lot of ways like when you leave your keys
by the door so that right as you walk out
the door, you bring your keys with you.
That's a, that's a way of structuring the
physical world to serve as a reminder that
to embed the constraint that you need to
leave with your keys in the physical space
itself And some of you may have realize
that you can think of these being Towers
of Hanoi and what's interesting thing
about this Towers of Hanoi is the kids
came where you can move circles between
pegs that look a lot like bagels. And what
we've done is we've turned this Towers of
Hanoi game into something where the, the
rules are the same. It's just the
representations changed and, and let's
play a game. We're gonna, we're gonna play
card games now. Two players, each of you
is gonna draw a number, one at a time such
that you have three numbers that add up to
fifteen. And your draw is without
replacement. So, if I pick five, that's no
longer available. For example, if I was
able to get four, five, and six together,
that add up to fifteen and that would be a
winning hand And let's say for example, I
picked five for starters and the other
player picks six so I pick three. And the
other player picks two And then I picked
seven. That would be a, a winning hand
And, this is hard enough for one pair. As
you can see, it's even harder to try and
play both sides. So we can make this a
little bit easier. So let's say instead of
having a b. Numbers imaginary in our head
will do the same thing but with playing
cards and so, I'm gonna be able to have
the number Ace, three, nine here or Ace,
three, nine. So, here we have a playing
cards Ace, two, nine. And again two
players and this time we can land in the
table so, so maybe so I can see him And
again start up by picking five And the
other player might pick six and so I'll go
three and at this point, especially if
other player can see my numbers and don't
know that seven is what I want next so
they're gonna go seven An d I'll go two to
prevent their fifteen and alright, now we
got a head off in another [inaudible]. So
and you can do And let's try, one, I
haven't thought it through but that, but
that might that might help and at this
point, I start to wonder whether, whether
this is gonna works. So, take, I'm not
really playing here but I'll take
Twelve:14 almost and, and it's kind of
nothing you can do at this point so no
dice A lot easier especially early on but
still somewhat challenging. Let's play
another game. We'll, we'll pick an easier
this time. How about Tic Tac Toe? So, this
is pretty easy. I think many of you know
this game so we can do x's in those. So we
can go x ad somebody can go o. We can do x
and o and x and o and x wins. That game is
a whole lot faster than either of the two
cards we play but what might shock you is
that these two games are [inaudible]. So,
I can fill in the numbers one, two, nine
and have them be exactly equivalent to our
card game. [sound] Any row or diagonal
that adds to fifteen also produces a
winning game in Tic Tac Toe. So for
example, I can pick this right column,
that's fifteen, fifteen all the way
through. And what we see from this is that
the way that you represent the problem
drawing numbers in our head, cards on the
table or numbers on the grid has drastic
influences on our ability to solve that
problem fluently and to see alternate
solutions and to be able to coordinate our
action with another person. And this is
why Herb Simon, the famous artificial
intelligence and cognitive science
researcher writes that solving a problem
simply means representing it so as to make
the solution transparent. For example if
you think about proofs in mathematics,
what's true at the end of the proofs is
also true at the beginning. The only thing
that's changed along the way is that the
Fact that the proof is indeed true has
been rendered clear to the reader. Why
were the oranges puzzle and the number
selection game so difficult? It's because
both of [inaudible] are working memory. We
have to keep in mi nd what moves are
possible, what numbers we held, what the
other person was thinking and maybe doing.
And that was a lot to keep in mind all at
once. Human beings are incredible in all
sorts of ways. Working memory is not one
of them. And one of the most important
things that we can do with user interfaces
by embedding the constraints of the
problem in the user interface itself is to
off load working memory so that those
limited resources become available for
other people. You may have heard the
famous a seven+ or -two as a limit of
working memory that we can keep seven+ or
-two things available at any point in time
And If not exactly true the real story is
a bit more complicated but if you wanna
have a rule of thumb to work with as a
designer, I suggest that two plus or minus
two that basically don't require users to
keep anything in mind that you can
possibly put on the screen. So far the
examples that we've looked at oranges,
bagels, cards, Tic Tac Toe are kind of toy
problems and you know they may make for
some good entertainment at a dinner party
but it's not real world stuff. They
demonstrate however principles of the
power of distributing cognition. That
absolutely has a real world impact. One
great example of this is the Task
Management System getting things done. Is
very much designed in the principles of
distributing cognition and mind. So, for
example, one of the rules of the getting
things done system is that whenever
something comes to your mind that you need
to do, the first thing you do is write it
down somewhere, anywhere and the reason
for that is if you have something in mind
that needs to be completed and you haven't
written it down yet, you're spending a lot
of cycles of working memory remembering.
To, I need to do my laundry to see if I
need to do my laundry. I need to do my
laundry and that's chewing up resources
that could be better deployed elsewhere.
Write it down if it gets out of your mind
and you can move on. One of the words that
people toss around all the time in terms
of effective user interfaces is that this
user interface is natural. And when we say
that, we mean a couple of different
things. But one of the things that we
mean, we can see in our example in our
oranges and bagels that the bagels as a
task is more natural because the
properties of the representation bagels
can stack matches the properties of, of
the thing that's being represented. One of
my user interfaces for this perspective is
the protease indigestible pill. This is a
pill that when you swallow it, it sends
out a little signal so that your, your
phone or the Internet knows that you've
taken this pill And, the, The ability of
keeping track of whether you have taken
the pill or not automatically by virtue of
taking the pill is a really natural user
interface that the ingestion act serves
both to take the pill and to mark that you
have done so. There's another example of a
really natural interaction in, in the
system which is that in addition to pill,
there's a, a transmitter that you need to
stick to your body And the transmitter has
a limited battery life. So, how do you
turn the transmitter on? It's a band aid
like system and the way that you turn on
the transmitter is you heal back the band
aid bandage and that turns it on And so
again, that action that you need to do to
stick it on yourself is exactly the same
action that you use to turn the peel on
And so by integrating the necessary step
with the step that's easy to forget. You
don't forget the step anymore. So let's
bring this back to normally user
interfaces. Here's an example of the print
dialog on a Macintosh And one of the
things that you can see here is that
there's a world in miniature strategy in
this print dialog box. So, if I wanna look
at the Stanford Academic Calendar I can, I
can print that here. And, what we're gonna
look at is, here's our world in miniature
where we see the entire legal sized page
shown inside the dialog box and one of the
things that, that makes clear is that I'm
not gonna be able to fit the top and the
bottom of the page. On a, on a letter
sized page because a letter sized page is,
is three inches shorter than the large
page and so consequently You know, it's
probably not something I wanna do And, one
of the things that I like about this is
that by showing you the world in
miniature, the challenges of working that
you've gotta decide here become much
clearer. Here's another example. This is
from Microsoft Word and what we can see
here is I'm again about to print this and
the dialog box that I get from word says a
foot of section one is set outside the
printable area of the page, do you want to
continue? And I can click Yes or I can
click no. Now, in order to answer this
problem, I need to know is it just that
the bounding box of the footer is outside
what the printer can print and so it's
irrelevant or is there actually content
that I need that won't be printed. None of
that is available from this dialog box And
so unlike the previous print dialog box
where we saw the world in miniature and
could see what was being cut off, here we
have no idea what, what's being cut off
And consequently, this is a much less
effect user interface And that's the end
of Part one.