We've all heard the saying that a picture
is worth ten thousand words. This idea of
worth is interesting because it implies
some kind of interchangeability. There are
some rate at which you can convert one
representation into another
representation. How might we establish
that interchangeability. One type of
interchange ability is informational
equipment. Two representations are
informationally equivalent if all the
information is present in one, can also be
inferred from the other But just because
the same information is theoretically
inferable doesn't mean it will take the
same required effort to extract it. Some
representations require more steps to
computing inference. And the difference in
the perceivers computational effort
presents both challenges and opportunities
for you as a designer. Let's look at an
example. Eight percent a pair of parallel
lines is cut by a transversal. This cut
generates eight angles. From the sentence,
it's difficult to reason about which pairs
form the alternate interior angles. And in
fact if you to try, you'll find yourself
creating a mental image of two parallel
lines cut by a transversal. With the
diagram like this however, the sentence in
the diagram are informationally equivalent
but computationally different for the
perceiver. One major benefit of the
graphical user interface over the command
line is that the graphical user interface
enables many common actions to be
perception tasks requiring little
inference. So far we've seen a number of
examples of how distributed cognition can
help individual work. Distributing how
ignition can also have powerful benefits
for group report and just to give you a,
a, a quick sense of what this might be
like. I'll give you an example from Ed
Hushon's research on airplane cockpits.
One of the things that observed is that
the artifacts in the cockpit help
coordinate action between the multiple
people that work there, the pilots. And so
for example, one, one instance of this is
the is the speed dial Where our landing
and takeoff. It's incre dibly important to
have the speed, be accurate because you
are at the most critical part of the, the
airplane. Your close to the ground, the
wings are designed for [inaudible]
designed primarily for going long and very
high and the shape of the wings have to be
changed to accommodate the lowest speed
that is required for landing and takeoff
and so, the multiple pilots on the large
airplane need to coordinate their efforts
and in several important ways. There are
several plastic indicators called bugs.
Around the perimeter of this speedometer
and the pilots can manually set those bugs
to do things like mark where a speed what
events will cause a change in the, certain
cause of change in the wing settings and
other things like that and what's nice
about these bugs is that they are visible
not just to the pilot that set them but to
everybody else in the cockpit also And so,
by remembering the by Making it triggers
for what will caused changes in action
manifest to everybody. These artifacts can
help coordinate collaboration and increase
safety in cockpit situations. So, what was
seen here is that when interface is
helping people distribute cognition, it
can encourage experimentation like we saw
in Tetris. It can scuttled learning and
reduce air, it's like we saw with the
[inaudible] blocks. It can show only the
differences that matter like in the
[inaudible] on the ground map. It can
convert slow calculation in the fast
perception like we saw with the map
coloring. It can support trunking
especially by experts as we saw with the
chess and with gesture interfaces. It can
increase efficiency as we saw with
diagrammatic representations and it can
facilitate collaboration like we saw in
the cockpit. Given all of these benefits
of good representations, it's kinda
surprising that a whole lot of actual
interfaces that are out there offer a
really crummy job at being able to help
people distribute their cognitive efforts.
So I call these four representations
common but deadly. Let's take a look at a
couple of them. Here's one. I was at a
symposium at IBM a couple of years ago. To
get on their Wi-Fi network, I needed to
enter a password. And, I typed in a
password that I thought would be just fine
and the Wi-Fi system told me, the password
you typed is not valid. Please change.
What do I need to change it to? The, all
passwords often have different
requirements like mixtures of upper and
lower case letters. The absence of numbers
or special modifier keys and, there's no
way for me to know from the screen what
the problem with the password that I
entered was. This representation would
obviously be a heck of a lot better if,
when I entered the password, it said, you
need a password that is at least ten
characters long and they contain the
mixture of upper and lower case characters
or that has at least one number. And that
could be validated the first time that I
check in the new password as supposed
[inaudible] till I type in both and hit Go
and it says, uh-uh. Here's another
example, NASA invited me to give a talk in
an event they had in San Francisco a year
or so ago and the registration for this
event was, this, this is the web form from
it and I, I thought I registered. I
clicked Go and after hitting Next, it said
you must fill out all registered fields.
You can see that at the top of the screen
right here and totally frustrating if you
try and register because you [inaudible]
well. Which one did I miss? It would be a
lot more effective if for example you
could highlight the things that you it
thinks you need to fill out or it could
create a smaller form that has only parts
that you missed the last time around and
says here is the one thing you needed to
fill that out before continuing. Here's
another example. This, this from BBEdit
and it when I tried to save it says,
document encoding mismatched. The document
contains data which describes its encoding
as UTFA. But the encoding has been set to
western, I saw Latin one and I have two
options here. One of them is cancel and
another one is save anyway. But the
actions that I'd lik e to be able to do
are probably something like. Make
everything UTF8 or make everything at one
or. A computer tell me which of these is
probably makes more sense, help me choose
between these or it doesn't matter but the
information that I need to be able to make
a decision simply isn't present in the
user interface, dialog box is should be
action oriented. They should help guide
towards users towards what their next step
is likely to be and you should provide
them with the information that they need
in order to be able to accomplish that
next step. Here's an interface that I
think is intentionally design to be
sub-optimal. Here we have the eBay funding
confirmation page and If you look at this
page, what you'll see is if you I switched
to a credit card and it says, before you
go to credit card we're gonna give you
this, this prompt that, that ask you to
verify that and, and eBay and PayPal do
this of course because they make use more
money if you see the bank account as
supposed you pay through credit card
transaction fee. And so down at the bottom
here it offers you two buttons. One of
them is pay with bank account and the
other one was pad with credit card. Good
action are in the titles, I really like
that part of this user interface. And what
you see is that the account that they want
you to pick is, is made nice and bright
and the account that you probably want is
dimmed out as if it's inactive. Is this is
a good user interface or bad user
interface? Well, user-experience is
probably somewhat degraded. Paypal's
profit significant increases and in a lot
of real world situations, you need them,
you may need to make this trade off. I, I
think that more globally there are other
ways that you could address this but I
thought this was an interesting example of
the interaction design that sacrificed
some user experience in order to achieve
higher profits. Hard to say whether it's
worth it. Here's a dialog box for
exporting a picture. We want to save that
to JPEG and the dialog box is notifying us
that this JPEG al ready exist. And you got
a couple of options so one thing that like
about thing that I like about this future
interface is that you get buttons that are
really action oriented here, that's great.
A challenge is, how do I know whether I
want this file or not? I mean, what is
l1010235.jpg. It would make a lot more
sense if this dialog box showed me an icon
of here's what here's what this picture is
and that way I could have a better sense
of whether I wanted to override it or skip
this operation or give it a brand new
unique name. Here's an example from
Microsoft Outlook. This is a duplicate
contact detected dialog box and it says
that he, you know the there's some
information here that already exist in
your contact. Do you wanna update it or do
you want to add this as a new contact. The
difficulty of course is, I don't know
what's in that contact right now and so
this is not a decision that I can make
from looking at this dialog box on its
own. I can of course click open existing
contact to show me that information but
that's one extra step down the line.
Microsoft improves this in a subsequent
version of Outlook. This dialog box is
probably still more complicated that it
really needs to be. I think it could be
streamline significantly but what it does
do is it shows me the two things that I
really need to know. The first of this
what the final outcome of the process is
gonna look like. So after we merge these
things, here's what you'll get. And the
other thing it's gonna show me is here the
piece of information that we're gonna
change in order to make that happen. One
way that I think this dialog box could be
stream line is that, well it shows that
the new, the final [inaudible] information
this way and it gives us the, so I can
change this or happening here. The old
contact information is shown in a
completely different format and so it's
difficult to compare. If you believe that
you don't need to see that information
because the relevance that certain here,
well then, just don't include this. If on
the other h and you decide that we do need
to show the old version because you may
wanna keep it, you know in that case it
probably make it a lot more sense to show
it in the manner that's parallel with
these other two boxes. What we've covered
in this past two lectures is understanding
of the theoretical foundations of how the
representation of information And have
tremendous consequences in terms of the
user experience of the system. I think
this is one of the most interesting topics
in all of ACI. And if you find this area
as interesting as I did, there is a couple
of books that I can recommend to go
further here. One of them is Herb Simons,
the science of the artificial. It is a
great monograph written several decades
now about the Role of design and science
and about the nature of mental
representations really interesting book.
Another one here is Ed Hutchins' book,
Cognition in the Wild which lays out a
foundation for distributed cognition. And
describes as work in airplanes and then
and on naval ships. [sound]. And the last
we have here is Don Norman's book, Things
That Makes Us Smart. Which is a, a great
book about a lot of cognitive science
research and distributive cognition and
the roles of representation in cognition
and this is one of the sources of, of
several of the examples in this lecture
like as what these other books too. I'll
see you next time.