In this video, we're going to talk about
Assigning Participants to Conditions. And
one of the most basic questions you can
ask about this is, should every
participant use every alternative? To
illustrate this, we're going to walk
through an example and we're going to see
the trade-offs that are intrinsic to
different approaches you can take here. In
this study, we're going to compare a smart
vacuum cleaner, with a more traditional
vacuum cleaner. As you remember from last
time, one of the first questions we should
ask about this are, what are the measures?
Do we want something that is, faster or,
cleaner or, less fatigue, better
ergonomics, lower environmental impact,
portability, ease of use, fewer errors.
Any of these are valid measures, you might
even keep track of them all. For our
example here though, we're, we're going to
pick two. We're going to go with faster,
and we're going to go with cleaner. So,
our manipulation is going to be vacuum
type and our measures are going to be
speed and cleanliness. To help illustrate
this example, I'm going to recruit the
help of my graduate students and TAs and
so here they are. One thing that you can
imagine is that you've assigned half of
them to each condition. That's called a,
between subjects design and so we could
assign half of them to the robot
interface. And we can assign half of them
to the traditional interface. So, Chinmi,
Nicolas and Alex get the robot and Dan,
Ranjitha and Jesse get the traditional
one. And let's say for example, that the
robotic interface performs better, faster,
cleaner. With only six people, it's hard
to say whether it's because the vacuum
cleaner there is better or whether the
three people we happened to assign to it
Chinmi, Nicholas and Alex were better
cleaners than Dan, Jesse, and Ranjitha.
So, the other strategy is that within
subjects design where we could have
everybody use both interfaces. Probably
going to use first. If they use the old
interface first, they've gotten practice
and they may be extra good or maybe tired
when t hey get to use the new one and
vice-versa .So, between subjects designs,
have a worry about individual differences,
within subjects designs, have a worry
about ordering effects. Is there some way
we can get the best of both worlds? Well,
how might we address these ordering
effects? Well, one thing we can do is we
can take half the people and have them try
one interface first. And the other part
and try the other interface first.
Counter-balancing has a couple of nice
properties. For starters, you can treat it
as completely a between subjects design if
you look at only the first task that
people do. And hopefully, the benefit that
you get from practicing or the detriment
of fatique is roughly the same in both
conditions and it'll even itself out. And
so, counter balancing washes out some of
those concerns. There are times where this
isn't the case and that's a great time to
use between subjects design. To minimize
learning effects, it's probably best to
make the first and second tasks different.
So in this case, we might have people
clean the D school as their first task and
clean the Gates building as their second.
This also has the added benefit of giving
us some more Ecological validity by trying
out a couple of different environments so
we know it's not just the Gates building
that's better cleaned by robots. It also
has the benefit that both the D school and
the Gates building are clean. How about
individual differences? Should we try to
balance for shirt color, hair length,
gender, or whether the picture in their
icon is squarish or more rectangular? It
depends on whether you think it's gonna
make a difference in the study or whether
one might plausibly believe that it would
make a difference in the study. Simplest
thing to do, is truly random assignment,
we'll talk about more sophisticated
techniques in a couple of slides. Okay, so
now we know a couple of ways of dealing
with two different alternatives, what if
we have three? With three alternatives,
you can use something called a Latin
Square. I'l l explain how this works in
three conditions, it generalizes more. In
a classic Latin Square design, each person
is going to use all three conditions.
You'll randomly divide your participants
up into three different groups. The first
group is going to get the first one first,
the second one second and the third one
third. The second group 231, and the third
one 312. So again, everybody gets all
three conditions, but their order changes.
And if you look at any particular ordering
segment, so like what people see first
what people see second what people see
third, you can see that, that is also
evenly balanced across the three
conditions. Whether you choose between
subjects approach or a within subjects
approach. The most important thing to do
is to make sure that the odds that any
particular participant ends up in a
particular condition or particular
condition ordering is completely random
is, is even. We can illustrate this with
an example. Say you wanted to find out
whether people were faster typing in the
morning or typing in the afternoon and you
allow people to come in whenever they
want. What if people who have a preference
for the morning, morning people are faster
typers than people who have a preference
for the afternoon? Your conclusion is that
morning would be, that morning was faster.
But that's not right, because just the
morning people were faster, not that
there's something about the, the morning,
or maybe not, you can't say confound. It's
possible that the causal reason was
population difference and not experimental
manipulation. This confound is why a lot
of economics is so hard. You're computing
correlations, but there's no manipulation.
Random assignment is tool number one in
achieving a, an effective manipulation. So
in our typing case, you would want to
assign people to be in either the morning
condition or in the afternoon condition.
The morning and afternoon example can seem
kind of stylized, but it shows up a lot in
the real world. For example, if you're
running a website, one easy thing y ou
might do is show everybody one alternative
on one day and one alternative on the
next. Well, there may be a difference
between those days. We'll talk more about
running experiments later on. But for now
I, wanted to point out that the key is if
you're going to do something like this
make sure that people are randomly
assigned. Easiest way in most cases is a,
is a between subjects design where you
assign people as they come in to see
either one interface or the other. Here's
another example of the importance of
random assignment. In the 1930's, some
studies were run at the Western Electric
Factory outside Chicago, called Hawthorne.
And the plan was pretty simple, find out
whether changes in lighting levels
affected productivity. So, experimenters
came in, raised the lighting levels,
productivity goes up. Then, they tried
lowering the light levels, productivity
went up. Tried a whole bunch of
combinations, after each intervention,
productivity went up. The conclusion of
course is that it's the active intervening
rather than that the light levels itself,
which was the major cause behind the
productivity change. Presumably either the
workers felt like people cared about them,
or the excitement of the experiment, or
whatever. That was the driving factor. In
recent years, some economists have
questioned whether in fact there was a
Hawthorne effect at the Hawthorne plant.
If you're curious, you can Google more
about that. In either case, the name stuck
and it means a case where what you're
seeing is your effect as a result of the
intervention rather than the thing you
were trying to study, and you can avoid
this with random assignment. We've talked
about counterbalancing the order of
conditions that participants experience.
You can also counterbalance how you assign
people the conditions. Say for example,
you are worried that typing speed will
differentially affect something in your,
in your interface. You're building a new
spreadsheet or something like that. You
could use a pretest to establish typing s
peed ahead of time and use that to assign
people to conditions. There's many
techniques for doing this. The simplest
way to do it is just look at high,
high-speed typers versus low-speed typers.
The key, no matter what, is that each
participant has an equal chance of ending
up in either condition. Let's walk through
an example. If you can pretest everyone
ahead of time, one slick thing that you
can do is form matched pairs. So, say we
get the typing speeds that we see here and
after ordering they look like this. We can
group them into pairs, and then for each
pair we can conceptually flip a coin about
which of them is going to land in which of
the two conditions. I got one of these
dollar coins in the ticket machine the
other day, it will do well for flipping,
so for a 35 and 37, it's heads. So, we'll
put 35 down here, in the first condition,
37 goes in the second. And for 57 versus
59, it's tails, so 59 goes here. Third
one's heads, so that gives us 61, 68. And
tails, and that gives us 99 goes here and
70 goes here. By doing this matched pairs,
you're balancing out the performance of
people approximately in each condition and
by having some randomness in there, you're
ensuring that you don't get some
accidental statistical artifacts that
creep in by saying assign all your odds
here and all your evens there. But say
people are coming in online so you can't
pretest people for the experiment. Well
what you can do, is you can pick some
threshold that you think is in about the
middle. So, for typing you might say 65
words a minute. And as people come in, you
can check whether they're above or below
that threshold and label them as high,
high or low, fast or slow typers based on
that. So, 35 we would say is low, 40 is
low, 90 is high, 68 is high and so on.
And, you can assign them to your two
different conditions, call them A and B by
high and low. So, our first low person to
come in 35, tails, so they go to B. And
then to balance that out 40 we would go
heads. Next time we got a pair of l ows,
we can flip the coin again and we're going
to do that for the highs also. So, the
highs come in and heads. So, our first
high will go to A and our second high will
go to B. You don't need to make sure that
you have even numbers of high and low
typers, unless you're worried about that,
making a material difference on the, on
the outcome. In fact, if you have enough
participants, you can look at this two by
two grid and compare the outcomes on the
four cells. What you do need to make sure,
is that there are the same number of fast
typers of high in A and in B and the same
numbers of slow typers are low in A and in
B. There's lots of ways that you can do
this kind of counterbalancing. In general,
all of them are treating the same thing
which is try and help the law of large
numbers that you get in a between subjects
study, work a little bit faster. Now,
there's a danger of assigning people based
on a pretest that I would like to warn you
about. Say, we wanted to pretest for coins
that were more likely to come up heads.
So, I have some coins here. I can flip
each of these a couple of times, heads,
tails. Okay, that one was heads more. So,
it's really heads more. Tails. Yes. That
was tails. Heads. And tails. So, we have
three coins that had a heady tendency and
three coins that had a taily tendency. Now
we can feed them a snack so we can get a
bagel. In fact, this is the same bagel
that's in the last lecture so with bagels
so it's, it's not such a fresh bagel
anymore but nonetheless, we think it'll
give our coin some sustinance so we can
each eat some of the bagel and we want to
see whether our heady coins become more so
and whether our taily coins become more
so. So, I think by the natural tendency of
these coins is in one direction by feeding
them, I, I think that may make them more
so. So, the question that we're going to
ask, is whether snacking increases the
natural tendency of coins. And we can
re-flip all of these and I, I won't
inflict that on you right now. But you can
try it yourself. And what you'll see of
course is that, none of these coins really
had a tendency towards heads or tails,
it's just that on a small number of
samples, you know, if you came out little
bit with more heads, if you came out
little bit with more tails. And if you
flip them again, there will be no
correlation between their heady tendency
in the first half and heady tendency in
the second half. To make it a little more
exciting than just the six coins that I
had in my pocket, I decided to generate 30
coins in Excel and I flipped them each 21
times and you can see the results here of
how many heads each got out of 21 tosses.
I picked an odd number so they would have
to be either heady or taily on the whole.
And what we can see if we rank them by
number, is it turns out actually, fifteen
of them had a head tendency, fifteen had a
tail. And the average of the, of the heads
is 12.9 and average of our tail tendencies
is 8.3. Now, after I feed them the snack,
I can flip that again. And, I've
highlighted in yellow and bolded again,
that the numbers that have a head
tendency. And there's essentially no
correlation between here. It does turn out
that our heads, have our, our initial
heads have an average of 10.7 after eating
the bagel. And our initials tails have an
average of 9.6. So, we can see that both
of these regress towards the mean. Both of
these are closer towards the expected
value of ten and a half. We may see a
perceived difference here between the 9.6
and the 10.7. In a future lecture, we'll
learn how to test whether that's a real
difference or whether that's a statistical
mirage. So, this danger of regression is
very real and it shows up all the time in
statistical analyses of things like low
performing schools increasing in the next
year or high performing schools
decreasing. The assignment problem that
results in regression to the mean, is when
you're making something like a dividing
line and you're using the assignment so
everybody who scores high goes up and
everybody who scores low goes down and
then you measure their performance
subsequently. If instead you use the
pre-test to counterbalance, like we did
with the typists, so we put high and
low-speed typists in both conditions, then
you no longer have that worry about
regression to the mean. So, the major
question that we tackled here is, should
every participant use every alternative?
And with it emerged was three major
strategies. In a Within-subjects design,
everybody tries all the options. This has
big benefits in terms of recruiting
participants. You get more work out of
each person. And it works really well when
you're not worried about learning or
practice or exposure issues. Trying one
version will pollute the other one. In
Between-subjects study, each person tries
one condition. This requires more people
and you may want to consider
counterbalancing for fair assignment. It
has the benefit of course, that each
participant is uncorrupted and for this
reason is the most common thing we see in
things like web studies. And if you use it
between subjects design, you can use
counterbalancing to help even things out.
What I am offering today, is just a really
high level overview. And I've necessarily
glossed over a whole bunch of important
details. But I wanted to give you a
initial lay of the land for running
studies. If you're interested in more,
more reading in this area, my favorite
book in this area is David Martin's book
Doing Psychology Experiments. I'll see you
next time.