I’d like to talk [about] an amazing creature: people.
In life, people are often seeking information.
That led to psychologist George Miller to describe people as “informovores”.
Informovores try to find and devour information, much like foragers seek and devour food.
And both informovores and foragers are trying to get lots of it quickly.
Pete Pirolli, a research scientist at PARC — and colleagues — has spent more than a decade
trying to figure out what features of information resources help or hinder
people’s ability to find out what they want.
One of the major attributes that informovores use to guide their searching
is what we call the “scent” of information:
As we browse the web, we are using cues of the pages that we look at
to try to figure out whether we can get to the information we want from where we are,
whether it’s trustworthy, whether it’s solving a problem.
And we’re also looking at these cues to figure out what options are available to us.
If you have a web page and you’d like to know whether the “scent” on the page is poor
for the people that come to that page or site, there are several telltale signs:
If you watch people  use your site, you can see them flail around when they get to a particular page;
they don’t know where to go.
Another technique — and one that Jared Spool and colleagues
have used successfully in user interface engineering — is to look at people’s confidence
as to whether they are on the right track, right before and right after they click a link.
Before tells you whether the link that you’re looking at is a good one — whether it has high “scent”.
And people’s confidence after tells you whether the page that you land on
beacons the informations that you’re trying to get to.
Another great way to tell when people are having trouble
with the scent  of information in how to follow the trail is the use of the Back button.
Lots of use of the Back button — major problems for your navigation.
Here’s an example of a menu bar of a web page that I think exhibits particular low scent.
This is the menu bar for the Stanford Federal Credit Union — a bank.
To give you a feel of what it looks like [interactively],
if you mouse over  any of these navigational elements, you’ll get a second level of navigation.
However, even with that second layer, this page exhibits many of the scent problems
that I think are common for low-scent pages.