In this lecture, we’re going to talk about trying out new interface with people and doing this on the way
that you can improve your designs based on what you learned.
One of the most common things the people asks when running studies is,
do you like my interface and it’s a really natural thing to ask but on some levels what we all want to know.
But this is really problematic on a whole lot of level.
For one it’s not very specific and so some people are trying to make this better
and so they’ll improve it by doing something like how much do you like my interface on one to five scale.
Or this useful interface?
Agree or disagree on one to five scale.
And this adds some kind of a patina of scientific-ness to it
but really it’s just the same thing you’re asking somebody do you like my interface?
And people are nice so they’re going to say sure I like your interface.
This, the please the experiment bias.
And this can be especially strong when our social or cultural
or power differences between the experimenter and the people that you’re trying at your interface with.
For example, in [inaudible] effecting India
where this effect was exacerbated when the experimenter was white.
Now, you should not take this to mean that you shouldn’t have your developers try out stuff with users.
Being the person who is both the developer and the person who is trying stuff out is incredible valuable.
And one example like a lot of this is Mike Krieger,
one of the Instagram founders is also former masters student in [inaudible].
And Mike when he left Stanford and join Silicon Valley,
every Friday afternoon he would bring people into the lab into his office
and have them try out whatever they were working on that week
and so that way they were able to get this regular feedback each week.
And, the people who were building on the system got to see real people trying them out.
This can be nails on the chart board painful, but you’ll also learn a ton.
So, how do we get beyond, do you like my interface?
The basic strategy that we’re going to talk about today is being
to use specific measures and concrete questions to be able to deliver meaningful results.
One of the problems of do you like my interface is compared to what.
And I think one of the reasons that people say yeah sure, is that there’s no comparison point.
And so, one thing is really important is when you’re measuring the effectiveness of your interface,
even informally, it’s really nice, to have some kind of comparison.
It’s also important to think about what’s the yard stick?
What constitutes good in this arena?
What are the measures that you’re going to use?
So how can we get beyond do you like my interface?
One of the ways that we can start out is by asking a base rate question like,
what fraction of people click on the first link in the search results page?
Or, what fraction of students come to class.
Once we start to measure correlation,
things get even more interesting like is there a relationship between the time
of day that classes offered and how many students attend it
or is there a relationship between the order of a search result and a click through rate.
For both students and [inaudible], there can be multiple explanations.
For example, if there are fewer students that attend early morning classes,
is that a function when students want to show up or
is that a good function on when good professors want to teach?
With the [inaudible] example, there are also two kinds of explanations.
If lower placed links yield fewer clicks.
Is that because the links are intrinsically poor quality or is it because people just click on the first link.
They don’t, they don’t bother getting to second one even if it might be better.
To isolate the effect of placement and identifying and explaining the cause of roll,
he needs to isolate that as a variable by saying randomizing the order of search results.
As we start to talk about these experiments, let’s introduce a few terms that are going to help us.
The multiple different conditions that we try, That’s the thing that we’re manipulating.
For example the time of the class or the location of a particular link on a search results page.
These manipulations are independent variables because they’re independent of what the user does.
They are in the control of experimenter.
Then, we’re going to measure what the user does and those measures are called Dependent Variables
because they depend on what the user does.
Common measures in HCI include things like to ask completion time.
How long does it take somebody to complete a task for example,
find something you want to buy, create a new account, order an item, Accuracy.
How many mistakes that people make and one of those fatal errors or those things
that they were able to quickly recover from?
We call how much the person remember afterward or after periods of nine years?
And emotional response, how does the person feel about the task being completed?
Were they confident?
Were they stressed?
Would the user recommend this system to a friend?
So, your independent variables are the things that you manipulate.
Your dependent variables are the things that you measure how reliable is your experiment.
If you ran this again, would you see the same result?
That’s the internal validity of the experiment.
So, have a precise experiment.
You need to be able to remove the confounding factors.
Also, it’s important to study enough people so that the results are unlikely to [inaudible] by chance.
You may be able to run this study, same study over and over and get the same result
but it may not matter in some real word sense and the external validity is the generalize ability of result.
That this supply only the 18-year-old in the college classroom or this is supplied to everybody in the world.
Let’s bring this back to HCI and talk about one of the problems here like interface as a designer.
I think one of the things that we commonly want to be able to do
is to be able to ask something like is my cool new approach better than the industry standard,.
Because after all that is why you’re making the new thing.
Now one of the challenges with this especially early
on the design process is that you may have something which is very much in its prototype stages
and something that is the industry standard is likely to benefit from years
and years of refinement and at the same time it may be stuck with years
and years of craft which may or may not be intrinsic to its approach.
So if you compare your cool new tool to Sun Industry standard, there’s two things varying here.
One is the fidelity of the implementation and the other one of course is the approach.
Consequently when you get the results,
you can’t know whether to attribute the result to fidelity, or approach, or some combination of the two.
So, we’re going to talk about ways of teasing a part of those different [inaudible] factors.
Now, one thing I should say right off the bat is there sometimes
where maybe less more relevant whether you have a good handling what the [inaudible] factors are.
So, for example, you’re trying to decide between two different digital cameras, at the end of the day,
maybe all you care about is image quality or usability and some other factor and exactly what the Makes
that image quality better or worse or any other element along the way maybe less relevant to you.
If you don’t have control over the variables, then identifying cause may not always be what you want,.
But when you’re a designer, you do have control over the variables and
that’s when it’s really important to [inaudible] the cause.
Here’s the example of a study that came out right when iPhone was released
done by research firm users center centric from this news article here Research firm use
as centric as release to study the trials to gauge how effective the iPhone’s unusual onscreen keyboard is.
The goal is certainly a noble, noble one but I cannot say the surveys approach results in data
that makes much sense Users centric broad in twenty owners of other phones.
Half had QWERTY keyboards, half had ordinary numeric phones with keypads.
None were familiar with the iPhone.
The research involved having the test subjects enter six sample test messages with the phones
that they already had and six with iPhone.
The end result was that the iPhone movies took twice as long
to enter text with an iPhone as they did with their own phones and made lots more typos.
So, let’s critique the study and talk about its benefits and drawbacks.
Here’s the web page directly from user centric.
What’s our manipulation study?
Well, the manipulation is going to be the input style.
And how about the measure in the study Is going to be the worst per minute.
And there’s absolutely value in being able to measure the initial usability of the iPhone For several reasons,
one is if you’re introducing new technology,
it’s beneficial and people are able to get up the speed pretty quickly.
However, it’s important to realize that this comparison is eccentrically unfair
because the users of the, the previous cell phones were experts at that input modality.
And if people who are using the iPhone or not [inaudible] modality.
And so, it seems quite likely that the iPhone users, once they become actually users,
are going to get better over time and so, if you’re not used to something the first time you try it,
that may not be a deal killer and it’s certainly not an Apple to Apple’s comparison.
Another thing that we don’t get out of this article is,
is this different significant so we read that each person typed six messages
in each of two conditions and so they did their own device in the iPhone
or vice versa six messages each and that the iPhone users were half the speed
or the mini rather than people typing with the iPhone were half
as fast as when they got to type with the mini qwerty, device they were accustomed to.
So this may tell us something about the initial usability of the iPhone.
In terms of the long use ability, long term usability you know I don’t think we get so much out this here.
If you are not satisfied by the initial data, you’re in good company.
Neither or the office to that study.
So, they want back a month later and they ran another study where they brought
in 40 new people t o the lab who were either iPhone users, QWERTY users or nine-key users.
And now, it’s more of an Apple to Apple’s comparison and not they’re going to test people
who are relatively experts in this three different modalities.
After about a month On the iPhone,
you’re probably starting to ask and thought in terms of your performance.
Definitely it gets better over time even past the month.
But you know a month starts to get more reasonable.
And what they found was that iPhone users and QWERTY users were about the same.
In terms of speed and, and that the numeric keypad users were much lower.
So, one again, our manipulation is going to be input style and we’re going to measure speed.
This time, we’re also going to measure error rate and what we see
is that iPhone users and QWERTY users are essentially the same speed.
However, The iPhone users make many more errors.
Now one thing I should point out of the study is
that each of the Different devices was used by different group of people.
And it was done this way so that each.
Each device was used by somebody who is comfortable and have experience with working with
that device and so we remove the worry that you have newbie’s working on these devices.
However, specially in 2007, there may have been significant differences
in who the people were who were using the early adaptors of the 2007 iPhone
or maybe business users were particularly drawn to the Qwerty devices or people who had better things
to do with their time than sending e-mail on the telephone or using the nine-key devices and so.
Well, this comparison is better than the previous one.
The potential for variation between the user populations is still problematic if what you would like
to be able to claim is something about the intrinsic properties
of the device and they, and this impart have to do with the users.
So what are some strategies for pair comparison?
To brain storm a couple of options, one thing
that you can do is insert your approach into a production setting and this may seem like a lot of work.
Sometimes it is but in the age of the web this is a lot easier than it used
to be and it’s possible even if you don’t have access
to the server of the service that you’re comparing against.
You can use things like a proxy server or client touch scripting
to be able to put your own technique and have an Apple to Apple comparison.
The second strategy for neutralizing environment difference between a production version
and your new approach is to make a version of the production thing in the same style as your new approach.
That also makes them equivalent in terms of their implementation fidelity.
A third strategy in one that’s use economy in research
is to scale things down so you’re looking at just a piece of system in a particular point in time.
That way you don’t have you worry about implementing a whole big giant thing,
you can just focus on one small piece and have that comparison be fair.
And the fourth strategy is that when expertise is relevant, train people up,
give them the practice that they need so that they can start at least hitting
that [inaudible] in terms of performance and you can get a better read than what it would be as newbie’s.
So, now to close out this lecture, if somebody asked you the question,
who’s interface acts better than the interface and why,
you know, you have a good start because we have a comparison.
However, you also know to be worried, what is better mean?
And often, in a complex system, you’re going to have several measures,
that’s totally cool, there’s a lot of value in being explicit though about what it
is that you mean by better, what are you trying to accomplish, what are you trying to improve?
And if anybody ever tells you that their interface is always better,
don’t believe them because nearly all the time the answer is going to be it depends.
And the interesting question is what does it depend on.
Most interfaces are good for some things and not for others.
For example, if you have a, a tablet computer where all of the screen is devoted to display,
that’s going to be great for reading, for web browsing for that kind of activity looking at pictures.
Not so good if you want to type a noble.
So here, we’re introduced control comparison
as a way of finding he smoking gun and as a way of inferring cause.
And often for when you have only two conditions,
we’re going to talk about that as being a minimal pair of design.
As a practicing designer, the reason to care about what’s [inaudible]
is that it gives you the material to make a better decision going forward.
A lot of studies violate this constraint and that gets dangerous
because it doesn’t, it, it prevents you from being able to make sound decisions.
I hope that the tools that we talked about today and
in the next several lectures we’ll help you become a wise and skeptic like our friend in this XKCD Comic.
I’ll see you next time.