Hi. In this lecture we're talking about
problem solving. And we're talking about
the rule that diverse perspectives play in
finding solutions to problems. So when you
think about a problem, perspective is how
you represent it. So remember from the
previous lecture. We talked about
landscapes. We talked about landscape
being able to represent the solutions
along this axis and the value of the
solutions. As the, as the height. And so
this is metaphorically a way to represent
how someone might think about solving a
problem. Finding high points on their
landscape. What we want to do is take this
metaphor and formalize it and part of the
reason for this course is to get Better
lodge, I can be able to think through
things in a clear way. So I'm going to
take this landscape metaphor and turn it
into a formal model. So how do we do it?
The first thing we do is we formally
define what a perspective is. So we speak
math to metaphor. So what a perspective is
going to be, is it's going to be a
representation of all possible solutions.
So it's some encoding of the set of
possible solutions to the problem. Once we
have that encoding of the set of possible
solutions, then we can create our
landscape by just assigning a value to
each one of those solutions. And that will
give us a landscape picture like you saw
before. Now most of us are familiar with
perspectives, even though we don't know
it. Let me give some examples. Remember
when we took seventh grade math? We
learned about how to represent a point,
how to plot points. And we typically
learned two ways to do it. The first way,
was Cartesian coordinates. So given a
point, we would represent it by and X and
Y value in space. So, it might be five
units, this would be the point, let's say
five, two, right? It's five units in the X
direction, two units in the Y direction.
But we also learned another way to
represent points, and that was Cartesian
coordinates. So we can take the same
point, and say, well, there's a radius,
which is its distance from the origin, and
then there's some angle theta, which says
how far we have to sweep out, in order to,
you know, sweep that arc, radius out in
order to get to the point. So two totally
reasonable ways to represent a point, X
and Y, R and theta. Cartesian, polar.
Which is better? Well, [laugh], the
answer, it depends. Let me show you why.
Suppose I wanted to describe this line, in
order to describe this line I should just
use [inaudible] coordinates I can just say
Y=3 and X moves from two to five. It's
really easy. [sound]. But suppose I wanna
describe this arc. If I wanna describe
this arc, now Cartesian coordinates are
gonna be fairly complicated, and I'd be
better off using polar coordinates.
Because the radius is fixed. And I just
talked about how the radius is, you know,
there's this distance R, and theta just
moves from, you know, A to B, let's say.
So depending on what I wanna do. If I
wanna look at straight lines, I should use
Cartesian. And if I wanna look at arcs, I
should probably use polar. So,
perspectives depend on the problem. Now
let's think about where we want to go. We
want to talk about how perspectives help
us find solutions to problems. And how
perspectives help us to be innovating.
Well if you look at the history of science
a lot of great breakthroughs. You know, we
think about Newton. You know, his theory
of gravity. You can think about people
actually having new perspectives on old
problems. Let's take an example. So,
Mendeleev. Came up with the periodic
table. In the periodic table he represents
the elements by atomic weight. He's got
them in these different columns. In doing
so, by organizing the elements by atomic
weight he found all sorts of structure.
Right, so all the metals line one column,
stuff like that, right? Remember that from
high school chemistry class. That's a
perspective, it's a representation of a
set of possible elements. He could've
organized them alphabetically. But that
wouldn't have made much sense. So
alphabetic representation wouldn't give us
any structure. Atomic weight
representation gives us a lot of
structure. In fact, when Mendeleev. You
know, wrote down all the elements that
were around at the time, according to
atomic weight. There were gaps in his
representation. There where holes for
elements that were missing. Those elements
became scandium, gallium, and germanium.
They were eventually found ten to fifteen
years later. After he'd written down the
periodic table, people went out and were
able to find the missing elements. That
perspective, atomic way. Ended up being a
very useful way to organize our thinking
about the elements. We do it all the time
now. When you have any sort of task,
you'll find that you're actually using
some sort of perspective. Suppose that
you're hiring someone. And you've got a
bunch of recent college graduates who
apply for a job. And you've gotta think,
okay, how do I organize all these
applicants, let's say, 500 applicants.
Well, one thing you could do is you could
organize them by GPA. You could take the
highest GPA down to the lowest GPA. That's
be one representation. And you might do
that, right, if you valued competence or
achievement. But you might also value work
ethic. And if that were the case you might
instead organize those same, you know,
CV's or application files by how thick
they are. Their gonna feel like really
think ones are people who work really,
really hard. They've accomplished a lot.
Well, the third thing you might do is you
might value creativity. And you might say,
"Well, let's put the ones that are sort of
most colorful, most interesting, over
here. And the ones that are least colorful
and least interesting over here." That's
the third way to do it. Now depending on
what you're hiring for, depending on who
the applicants are, any one of these might
be fine. The only point I'm trying to make
here is that there's different ways to
organize these applicants. In each one of
those ways you organize, whether it's in
your head, or whether it's formally laying
them out in some way. Is a perspective.
And those perspectives will determine how
hard the problem will be for you. Let me
explain why. Now I wanna take, I wanna go
back to the landscape metaphor. And when I
think of that landscape as being rugged,
and by rugged I mean that it's not, it
doesn't look like a single peak. That
there's lots of peaks on it. And I want to
formalize this notion of peaks. And I do
so as follow. I'm going to define what I
call a local optima. A local optima is a
point such that, if you look at the points
on either side of it, they're lower in
value. So it's sort of a point that
locally is the highest possible value. So
if I look at this particular rugged
landscape again, there's three local
optima, one, two, three. So at any one of
these three points, I'd be stuck. I
couldn't, if I looked to the left or to
the right, I wouldn't find a solution
that's better. A perspective is gonna be,
a good perspective is gonna be a
perspective that doesn't have many local
optima. A bad perspective is gonna be one
that has a lot of local optima. Let me
give you an example, okay? So, suppose I'm
coming up with a candy bar. Suppose I'm
tasked with coming up with a new candy
bar. So I have my team of chefs make a
whole bunch of different, you know,
confections for me to try, and I want to
find the very best one. So many of them,
there's so many possibilities, not even
sure how to think about it. But one way to
represent those candy bars might be by the
number of calories that they have. So I
can organize all the different things they
make by number of calories. And if I did
that, maybe I'd have three local optima.
So that's a reasonable way to represent
these possible candy bars. Alternatively,
I might represent those candy bars by
masticity, which is chew time. Like, how
long it takes to chew'em. So these would
be the ones that maybe only take two
minutes to chew. And these may take twenty
minutes to chew. Well, chew time is
probably not the best way to look at a
candy bar. And so, as a result, I'm gonna
have a landscape with many, many more
peaks. And so, because it's got many more
peaks, that's more places I could get
stuck. So it's not as good of a way to
represent the possible solutions. It's not
as good a perspective. The best
perspective would be what we call a Mount
Fuji landscape, the ideal landscape that
just has one peak. And these are called
Mount Fuji landscapes, because if you've
ever been to Japan, and you look at Mount
Fuji, it looks pretty much like this. It's
actually not quite like this, there's like
snow on the top. But for the most part, it
looks just like one giant cone. If you're
on a Mount Fuji landscape, if you're
sitting at some point, you can always just
climb your way. Right up to the top. So
these single peak landscapes are really
good because, you've basically taken a
problem. And made it very, very simple.
What would be an example of a Mount Fuji
landscape? I'm gonna take a famous
example. So, a famous example comes from
scientific management, and due to
Frederick Taylor. Taylor famously saw for
the optimal size of a shovel. So let's
think about the shovel size landscape. So,
on this axis, I've got the size of the
shovel. And on this axis, I've got the
value. What do I mean by the value? I
don't mean how much I can sell the shovel
for, I mean it's like how useful the
shovel is at the task. So let's suppose
we're shoveling coal and I want to think
about how many pounds of coal can some
shovel in a day as a function of the size.
So let's start out here where the size is
zero. So this is the size of the pan. If I
have a shovel has a pan of size zero,
that's commonly known as a stick and we
can. Get anything. We're not gonna shovel
anything with a stick. Well, if I make it
bigger, you know, make it the size of,
maybe, like, a little spoon or something,
then we can shovel a little bit. And as I
make the shovel bigger and bigger and
bigger, we, whoever, my workers, can
shovel more and more coal. But at some
point, the shovel's gonna get a little bit
too big. And it's gonna be too heavy to
lift. And the worker's gonna get tired,
and I'll shovel, he'll shovel less and
less and less and less. And then
eventually get to some point where the
shovel's so big that he can't even lift
it, and it's as useless as the stick. So
if I look at value in terms of how much
coal the person can shovel in a day is a
function of the size of the shovel. I'm
gonna get a single peaked landscape.
That's gonna be an easy problem to solve.
And this idea, that we could represent
scientific problems in this way. Where
mechanical engineering comes in this way
and then climb our way to peaks, is the
basis is something called scientific
management and it was the idea was that
you could then by finding these high
points on these landscapes, find possible
solutions. We're only going to find out a
solution, right, for sure if you hill
climb like this if it's single peaked. If
it's rugged and looks like this mess,
looks like Mount Fuji landscape you're
fine, but if it looks like this miss,
mess, this city landscape, if you have a
bad perspective, well then if you climb
hills you could get stuck. Just about
anywhere, so what you'd like is you'd like
a Mount Fuji landscape and in the case of
simple things like this shovel. That's
easy to get. Let me give you another
example. This one's a lot of fun. This is
a favorite game of mine called Sum to
fifteen and was developed by Herb Simon
who's a Nobel Prize winner in economics.
And Sum to fifteen was developed to show
people why diverse perspectives are so
useful and different ways of representing
a problem can make them easy, can make
them like Mount Fuji or can make them
difficult. Okay? So here's how Sum to
fifteen works. There's cards numbered from
one to nine face up on a table. There's
nine cards in front of you. Each, there's
two players, each person. Takes turns,
taking a card. Until all the cards are
gone possibly right, it could end sooner,
if anybody ever holds three cards that add
up to exactly fifteen they win. That's the
game. So release up to nine cards.
Alternate taking cards. If you ever get
exactly three that sum to fifteen you win.
So let me show you a game. Here's a game
between two people, call them Paul and
David. Paul goes first, now you'd think
when you play this game the thing to do
would be to choose the five. Paul chooses
the four, which is sort of an odd choice.
David goes next so he takes the five. Paul
then takes the six. Now the six is a
strange choice because four plus six plus
five equals fifteen. So it looks like
there is no way that he can win. Well this
will be confusing to Doug. So Doug's gonna
take the eight. Now notice eight plus
five, oops, equals thirteen. So that means
Paul has to take the two. So he takes the
two. Well think about what happens next.
Four plus two is six, so if Doug doesn't
take the nine, he's gonna lose. But six
plus two, is eight. So if Doug doesn't
take the seven he's gonna lose. So what
you've got here, is that Paul's won. No
matter what Doug does, Paul's gonna win
the game. Now this is a pretty tricky
game, right? It was developed by a Nobel
Prize winner. You could imagine there's
lots of strategy involved. I wanna show
you this game in a different perspective.
Remember the magic square from seventh
grade math? Every row adds up to fifteen:
eight+3+4, one+5+9, six+7+2. So does every
column: eight+1+6 sums up to fifteen;
three+5+7 sums up to fifteen. And even the
diagonals: eight, five, two is fifteen;
six, five, four is fifteen. Every row,
every column, every diagonal sum up to
fifteen. Let me show you this game again
on the Magic Square. So, just a different
perspective on sums of fifteen. Paul goes
first, and takes the four. Doug goes next
and takes the five. Paul takes the six,
which is an odd choice, because now he
can't win. Doug then takes the eight, Paul
blocks him with the two. But now it turns
out, either the nine or seven will let
Paul win. What game is this? You're right,
it's tic tac toe. Sum to fifteen is just
tic tac toe, but on a different
perspective, using a different
perspective. So if you turn sum to
fifteen, if you move the cards one to nine
and put them in the magic square, what you
do is you create a Mount Fuji landscape.
In a sense, right? You make the problem
really simple. So a lot of great
breakthroughs, like the periodic table,
Newton's Theory of Gravity, those are
perspectives on problems that turned
something that was really difficult to
figure out into something that suddenly
makes a lot of sense. Very easy to see the
solution. At least it?s something I call
in my book, one of my books, the
difference, I call this the savant
existence theorem. For any problem that's
out there, there exists some way to
represent it, so that you turn it into a
Mt. Fuji problem. Now, why is that? Well,
it's actually fairly straightforward. All
you have to do is, you know, if you've got
all the solutions here represented on this
thing, you put the very best one in the
middle. And then put the worst ones at the
end. And then just sort of line up the
solutions in [inaudible] A, so that you
turn it into a Mount Fuji. So it's very
straightforward. Now the thing is, in
order to make the Mount Fuji, you'd
already, you'd have to know the solution
already. This isn't a good way to solve
problems but the point is, it exist. So
it's always the possible that someone
could look at particular problem and said,
hey what if thing of it this way? And
doing so turn something that was really
rugged into something now Fuji. Here is
the flip side though. There is a ton of
bad perspectives. So just like there's
these Mount Fuji perspectives, there's
also lots and lots of horrible ways to
look at problems. Think about this.
Suppose I have just, you know, ten
alternatives and I wanna think about what
are all the different ways I can just put
them in a line. Well there's ten things I
could put first, nine things I could put
second, eight things I could put third and
so on. So there's ten times nine times
eight times seven times six times five
times four times three times two times one
perspectives. Most of those. Are going to
not be very good. They're not going to
organize this set of solutions in any
useful way. Particularly they're not going
to, only a few of them are going to create
Mount Fujis. So we think about the value
of perspective, what we get is, there's
really good ones out there. That
insightful, smart people can come up with
really good representations of problem to
make the landscapes less rugged. If we
just think about things in random ways,
we're likely to get a landscape that's so
rugged that we're going to get stuck just
about everywhere. We're not going to be
able to find good solutions to the
problem. And we're going to get things
that look like domesticity landscape,
where we're going to get things with lots
and lots of P. Let's move on now and talk
about how we move on these landscapes. So
once I got our landscape, how do I find
better solutions? Are there other
alternatives to just sort of climbing a
hill? Because that hill climbing idea
really only works in one dimension. What
if I've got all sorts of dimensions? How
do I think about. [sound]. So what have we
learned? First thing we've learned is that
when you go about trying to solve a
problem, when you encode it in some way,
that's a perspective. And a perspective
creates peaks, right, it creates these
local optima. So a better perspective has
fewer local optima. Worse perspectives
have lots of local optima. And if you
think about how many perspectives are out
there, we just saw there's billions of
them. Because there's billions of
perspectives, most of those probably
aren't very useful. Some of them, though,
turn problems into Mount Fujis. And
sometimes it takes a genius. It takes a
Newton, it takes a Mendeleev, to come up
with a way of representing reality so that
something that was incredibly rugged
becomes Mount Fuji like. Other times, if
you think about the size of a shovel, that
problem most of us could probably figure
out a way to represent that problem just
by shovel size, so that it becomes a Mount
Fuji. The big point is this. When we go
about solving problems, the first thing we
do is we encode them. We have some
representation of the problem. That
representation determines how hard the
problem will be. If we represent.
[inaudible] Effectuated it's a Mount Fuji,
it's easy. If we run it, represent it
sectionally with that masticity landscape,
it's probably gonna be fairly hard. Where
we wanna go next, is we wanna talk about
once we've got this representation of the
possible solutions, once we have that
landscape, so to speak, how do we search
on that landscape? So one thing we've
talked about was climbing hills. But
there's lots of different ways you can
climb hills. That's what we'll talk about
next, the heuristics we use on a
landscape. Thanks.