Hi, in this set lectures we are going to talk about problem solving.
We are here to talk about individuals and teams go about solving problems.
We are here to focus on a couple of things.
We're going to talk about the role that diversity plays in problem solving,
and were also going to talk about how ideas can get recombinded.
How a lot of innovation comes from somebody having an idea in one place, and it  being applied someplace else.
Those are going to be the two main themes:
The role of diversity, and the power of recombination.
So to get there, think about how we model problem solving.
We got to start off by making it more formal,
constructing a somewhat formal model.
So here is how we are going to do it:
We are going to assume you take some sort of action (a),
where you have some sort of solution (a),
and there's a payout function (F) that gives you the value of that particular action.
That action could be a particular string of code
if you are writing computer code, and (F) might be how fast that code runs.
Alternatively,  (a) could be a health care policy
and (F) would be how efficient that health care policy is.
So, (a) is the solution that you propose
and F(a)  (F of a)  is how good the solution is.
What we want to do is somewhat understand how people come up with better solutions,
and where innovation comes from.
So to do that we are going to invoke a metaphor.
And we are going to use this 'metaphor of a landscape' as a lens through which to interpret our models.
Okay, so, think about it in the following way.
You are trying to come up with some solution to a
problem, and each solution has a value.
So the altitude here is the value of it.
So,  B   is the best possible solution.
Now, along here on the X-axis are all the different solutions.
So I might start out having some Idea (I)
(Let’s just put it right here, and here’s my idea.)
and it's an okay idea;
but we would like to think about how we find better ideas?
So one think you might do is
you might sort of try things to the left and the right,
and realize that  sort of climb uphill here
and you get to some point (C)
and (C) might be where I get stuck,
because if I go to the left I’m lower,
and to the right I’m lower,
so I can say “Wait, (C) is the best thing I can come up with.”
What we want to see is  how people come up with these ideas,
how teams of people come up with better ideas,
and how we can avoid getting stuck on (C),
and possibly getting myself up to (B).
How are we going to do it?
Well, here’s what the model is going to look like:
We are going to start out by talking about
something I am going to call ‘perspectives’.
What is a perspective?
Perspective is how you represent the problem.
So if someone poses some problem to you—
again, whether it is code, health care policy,
designing a bycicle, or designing an addition to you house—
you have some way of representing the problem in your head.
That's going to be a perspective,
literally how you encode the problem.
Once you have encoded the problem, what you do is
you create—again, this is metaphorically—a ‘landscape’.
as if you can think of your encoding is like that horizontal axis,
and that there is a value for each possible solution,
and that creates a landscape.
So we are going to talk about how different perspectives
give different landscapes.
That is the first part.
[The] second part is something I’m going to call ‘heuristics’.
Heuristics are how you move on the landscape.
So, remember when I drew that landscape,
I talked about climbing up the 'hill'.
Well, 'Hill Climbing' is one heuristic.
'Random Search' would be another heuristic—
if you just randomly pick some points
and then find which one is where the highest value is—
That is another heuristic.
So we will talk about
how different perspectives and different heruistics
allow people to  find a better or improving solutions to problems.
So that is going to be the focus of our model of problem solving.
People have perspectives, and people have heuristics.
Once we finish talking about individuals,
then we will talk about teams.
One of the interesting things is if you have groups of people
or teams of people solving a problem.
You actually can show that they will be better
than the individuals in it.
And the reason why is because they have more tools,
and those tools tend to be diverse.
So they have different perspectives and different heuristics,
and all that diversity makes them better
coming up with new solutions and better solutions to problems.
So, teams are going to be important.
After we have talked about teams,
and after we have talked about the role of
how one person can improve upon the solution of another,
we are going to extend our model a little bit
and talk about  recombination.
So here is sort of the big idea. The big idea is this:
I have some solution from one problem,
you have a solution from a different problem,
and sometimes I can take your solution and combine it with my solution,
and come up with something even better.
So, the thing about sophisticated products—
like a house, an automobile, or even a computer—
that consists of all sorts of solutions to sub-problems.
And we are going to see how
by recombining solutions to sub-problems
we get ever better solutions, and that is a big driver of innovation.
So let us think back for a second.
Remember on our previous lecture,
we talked about how without sustained innovation
we no longer get growth,
that growth depends on sustained innovation.
What I am going to talk about here is
how diversity leads to innovations,
and how recombinations of innovations  can lead to even more Innovations.
So that is the big theme.
So that is where we are headed.
We are going to start by  talking about perspectives.
Then we will talk about heuristics.
Then we will talk about how teams of people
can leverage their diverse perspective in heuristics.
The we will talk about recombining ideas can really drive a lot of growth.
All right, let’s get started.
Thank you!