Hi... Remember we were talking about
problem solving. We talked about, when you
first solve a problem, what you do is come
up with a perspective, a way of
representing the set of solutions. Then we
talked about how you use heuristics to
search among those possible solutions,
given your representation. And we've seen
how having lots of heuristics and diverse
heuristics can help you find, look at more
points, and find, possibly find better
solutions. What we wanna do in this
lecture, is combine those two ideas,
perspectives plus heuristics, to show why
teams of people. Can often find solutions
to problems that individuals can't. That
why teams are better. Now I say teams, I'm
gonna use this in a very loose sense. I
don't necessarily mean, a team of people
sitting in a room and brainstorming. That
sort of stuff. What I mean is, a
collection of people, possibly you know,
working even over time. So even if it's
something like your toaster on your
counter, you can think of that as being
something that's been really consistently
and constantly improved upon by a team of
people. So there's the person who first
invented the toaster. Then somebody
improved it. Then somebody come up with
the crumb tray. Then somebody came up with
the automatic shut off. And all sorts of
things, right? So a toaster consists of a
whole bunch of improvements. And you can
think of that as being. That current
solution we have is being something that
the team has come up with. So again, by
team I don't necessarily mean a group all
working together and in some unit. You
just need a collection of people. So how
does it work? Why are teams and why are
groups of people better than individuals?
Well, let's go back and let's think about
the, the candy bar example. Remember I had
one landscape, one perspective based on
calories, and that had three local peaks,
right? And, well, let's represent those by
A, B and C. And then I had another
landscape that was represented by
masticity, and that had five peaks. And we
can call these, let's call these A, B, D,
E and F. So, these are different than the
peaks for the caloric landscape. With the
one exception. Notice for sure that A,
which is the best possible point, that has
to be a point in the caloric landscape and
it's also gotta be a peak in the masticity
landscape. And that's because it's the
best possible point. So it's the best
possible point, it's gotta be a point in
every landscape. Now we can characterize
these problem solvers. By their local
peaks, by their local optimum. So, the
local optimum of the caloric landscape are
A, B, and C. The local optimum for the
domesticity landscape are A, B, D, and F.
And we remember we said that the caloric
landscape was a better landscape than the
masticity landscape. Because of the fact
that it had fewer local optima. So one way
to figure out how good you are at solving
a problem is how many local optima you
have given your perspective and your
heuristic. Now here was something the
heuristic, right? Is just hill climbing.
Let's go deeper. Cuz that's just a, that's
a fairly crude way of thinking about how
good a problem solver is. We can actually
take into account, the average value of
those peaks. So the piece where people get
stuck are A, B, C, D, E, and F. And we can
assign a value to each of those. So
suppose the value of A is ten, B is eight,
and so on. So A is the out local op, the A
is the global optimum, and some of these
other peaks aren't so good. Well we can
usually can ask, what's the average value
of a peak for the caloric problem solver?
So the problem solver who thinks in terms
of the caloric perspective, then gets
stuck at A, B, and C. What's the average
value? Well, A has a value of ten. B has a
value of eight. C has a value of six. And
so, we're gonna give the abilities as the
average of those three peaks, which is
eight. But if I look at the masticity
problem solver, they get stuck at, at A,
B, D, E, and F. And those have values ten,
eight, six, two, and four. And the average
of those is six. So when you think about
the ability of the masticity problem
solver as being six. So not only did it
correct problems of our local optima. They
had higher average values. This is another
reason why that person's a better problem
solver. Let's think of them now, though,
as working as a team. I think, in the
working as a team, the caloric problem
solver gets stuck at A, B, and C, the
domesticity problem solver gets stuck at
A, B, D, E, and F. Let's suppose, first,
[inaudible] problem solver works on the
problem first, and she gets stuck at B.
She then passes the problem to the
[inaudible] problem solver. And the
[inaudible] person says, well, you know
what? I can't help you, because B looks
pretty good to me. Because B is also a
peak for him. Suppose instead, though,
that the caloric problem solver gets stuck
at C. And she passes C on to the masticity
problem solver. And now this masticity
person, C, if you notice, isn't anywhere
in this list. C is [inaudible] optima.
That means that the masticity person can
get from C to some other local optima. And
it's gotta be one that's better. Why does
it have to be better? Because she's, this
person's hill climbing, if he's hill
climbing, then he's got to be able to find
something that's better than C and that's
going to be either A or B. So the
intersection of these local optima A and B
are the only places where they can get
stuck. If, for example, the [inaudible]
person went first and got stuck at E, then
the [inaudible] person could take E and
get to someplace else, either A, B or C.
If she gets to A or B the masticity person
is also stuck. If she gets to C, then the
masticity person can then in turn take it
up to A or B so the only places that the
team can get stuck is A or B. If you make
this form up called the intersection
property that the local optima for the
team is the intersection of the local
optima for the individuals. So, if we look
at the team, there's only two places the
team can get stuck, ten and A, and the
average value there is nine. So, the
ability of the team is higher than the
ability. Of either person. And the reason
why is because the team's local optima is
the intersection of the local optima for
the individuals. So the reason why, then,
we see over time products get better, the
reason why we see teams being really
innovative, the reason why we see a lot of
science being done by teams of people is
because the only place a team can get
stuck is where everybody on the team can
get stuck. So this very simple model,
having perspectives and heuristics, can
explain, why is it the case that teams are
so much better than individuals? And why,
over time, we keep finding better and
better solutions to problems. It's not
necessarily that we're getting smarter.
Now, it's true, we are coming up with new
ways to represent problems. And we also
are coming up with all sorts of new
heuristics all the time. We're developing
new ways to solve problems all the time.
But another thing that's going on, is,
just because of the accumulation of so
many different ways of looking at
problems, and so many different ways of
trying to solve them, that we get the
intersection. Of all those peaks and that
gives us better solutions. So here's the
big claim. The team can only get stuck at
a solution that's a local optima for
everyone on the team. That means the team
has to be better than the people in it. So
what we want, right, you want people with
different local optima. You want people to
get stuck in different places. Well how do
we get it? We don't. We've already looked
at this twice, right? We looked at it
first perspective perspectives. So if you
coat it this way and I coat it this way,
then we're going to get stuck in different
places. We also want people with different
heuristics. If I look in this direction
and this direction, and you look in this
direction and this direction, and we add
us together, we look in all four of those
directions. So what we want, is we want
diverse perspectives, and we want diverse
heuristics. And that diversity will give
us different local optima, and those
different local optima will mean that we
take the intersections, and we end up with
better points. That's sort of the big
idea. So if we take, again, let's play
this out in more deals. And imagine we've
got these, just, here's this set of
solutions. If one of us looks like this.
And one of us looks maybe two to the left.
And one looks two down. And one looks to
the north, south, east and west. If we
have all of these different, you know,
maybe one person looks two over this way,
all these different heuristics looking at
the problem that means we're less likely
to get stuck at the same point. Which
means the team is going to do better. Or,
over time, society is going to do better
finding solutions to problems. This all
seems really smooth and nice and great and
we've seen, teams are better, we see the
value of diverse perspective, we see the
value of diverse heuristics. But what's
missing? Cuz this seems highly stylized.
There's two things that I've left out.
First one is [sound] right, we can write
this down as communication. I've assumed
that when you've got a team solving a
problem that they can communicate their
solutions to one another right away. Now
that's not always the case. There's a lot
of misunderstandings going on and we might
not listen. I might just say, no I'm not
listening. I'm not listening, right? And
no matter what you say we don't find a
better solution. And think of something
like the toaster though, it's weird, we
can communicate through the toaster. If I
come up with a better toaster and I make
it, then you can look at my solution and
know what I've done and then you can add
the crumb tray. So think about making an
artifact, the artifact itself, the
artifact is the solution. That gets
communicated right away, but generally
speaking communication can be a problem.
The other thing I've assumed is that.
There is the possibilities that an error.
In interpreting the value of a solution.
So, I'm assuming if somebody proposes a
solution and its better, we instantly know
it. It's as if there's some sort of oracle
we can go to and say, oh yip, that's a
better solution. That may not always be
the case. So it could be that I could do
something really interesting and people
just think no, it's a bad idea. They make
an error in terms of whether or not its
interesting thing or it could be that I
propose something that's worse, and people
think oh that's a great idea and then we
actually look and it's not a good idea. So
I've assumed there no errors in
determining the value of the solution, and
when somebody proposes this solution, you
know exactly what it's worth. That's not
always going to be the case. So it's won't
always be true that there's perfect
communication in this perfect evaluation.
So, in a Ricksher model, we could include
communication error. And that's going to
hurt teams. And we can also include just
errant evaluation. That's also going to
hurt teams. Even so, right, this power,
this model has shown us something fairly
powerful, which is that diverse
representations of problems in diverse
ways of coming up with solutions can make
teams of people better able at coming up
with solutions than individuals. And it
also sort of told us where innovation is
coming from, right? Innovation is coming
from different ways of seeing problems,
and different ways of finding solutions.
There's a lot going on, right? And now,
I've got this model of problem solving,
and when you think about people finding
solutions to particular problems. Now we
want to step back a bit in the next
lecture when I think about, what about
bigger things like designing a house,
designing a car, designing a railway
system, designing a city, the bigger
problems. Well, often times those bigger
problems, the solutions, you would think
of a, like making a computer. The computer
may consist of the solutions to a whole
bunch of sub-problems. So where we want to
go next is you want to talk about how we
combine solutions to come up with new
solutions. And we'll see how that can even
be used as an argument to where economic,
where economic growth comes from. It
actually comes from individual solutions
being recombined. Okay, thanks.